<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The worthy communicant rewarded Laid forth in a sermon, on John 6.54. Preached in the Cathedrall of St. Peter in Exeter, on Low-Sunday, being the 21. of Aprill, Anno 1639. By William Sclater, Master of Arts, late Fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge, now chaplaine of the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Bishop's Barony of Saint Stephens, and preacher also at S. Martin, in the same city.</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836792</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836792</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11610)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1187:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The worthy communicant rewarded Laid forth in a sermon, on John 6.54. Preached in the Cathedrall of St. Peter in Exeter, on Low-Sunday, being the 21. of Aprill, Anno 1639. By William Sclater, Master of Arts, late Fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge, now chaplaine of the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Bishop's Barony of Saint Stephens, and preacher also at S. Martin, in the same city.</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Y[oung] for G. Lathum at the Bishops head in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1639]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1079:1"/>
            <p>THE WORTHY COMMUNICANT REWARDED LAID FORTH IN A SERMON, ON JOHN 6.54. PREACHED IN THE Cathedrall of St. PETER in Exeter, on Low-Sunday, being the 21. of Aprill, <hi>Anno</hi> 1639.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>WILLIAM SCLATER,</hi> MASTER Of Arts, late Fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge, now Chaplaine of the Right Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God the Lord Biſhop's Baronry of Saint Stephens, and Preacher alſo at S. Martin, in the ſame City.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 COR. 11.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall eate this Bread, and drinke this Cup of the Lord unworthily, ſhall be guilty of the Body and Bloud of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. apud P. Lumb. l.</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 9. <hi>C.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Non manducans manducat, &amp; manducans non manducat, quia non manducans ſacramentaliter, aliquando manducat ſpiritualiter, &amp; è converſo.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. Y.</hi> for G. LATHUM at the Biſhops head in Pauls Church-yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1079:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1079:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL Doctor PETERSON, Dean, and Canon reſidentiary of St. Peter in Exeter, Chaplaine in ordinary to his Majeſty, &amp;c. my worthily honoured friend, the exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berancie of all bleſsings.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which was graced with your audience, in preaching, with your thanks, when prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, be pleaſed now to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour with your noble Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage in print; which is a kind of preaching too, that, as<note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 18.23.</note> 
               <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> did <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhi,</hi> and Saint<note n="b" place="margin">John 20.4.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> doth [out-run] the vocall, by ſo much farther, as it can lengthen out its ſtrides (as <hi>Procruſtes</hi> ſtretched his gueſts, in<note n="c" place="margin">Plutarch. in vita Theſei.</note> 
               <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that were for his bed otherwiſe too ſhort) to reach it ſelf unto the hands, and eyes of thoſe good Catholike Chriſtians, unto whoſe ears my voice, had it bin Stentorian, or as a<note n="d" place="margin">Mar. 3.17.</note> Boanerges, could not come: To preach by the pen, which in the expreſsion of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
<pb facs="tcp:1079:3"/> Alexandrinus</hi> is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is as uſefull ſometimes as to doe ſo by the tongue; and this inſtruction by the<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>—</note> hand, like to a wedge of gold beaten into a plate, ſpreads more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and often with as large emolument to the Church, as that which is by lively<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. lib. prim. Strom.</note> ſpeech, or ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cination. I may ſeeme perchance by this to light a candle to the Sun, and to cast my ſpoonfull into that vaſt Ocean of knowledge, which we (though ſitting upon the very lees and dregs of time for Atheiſme and ill practice, which with bleeding hearts we view abroad, and wonder at) have lived to ſee make up that propheſie of great Daniel, who foretold it ſhould
[<note n="g" place="margin">Dan. 12.4.</note> abound]; and of the Kingly Prophet, whoſe prediction is now at its full height, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of accompliſhment, God gave the word, and great are the company of the<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 68.11.</note> Preachers; when thus comparatively I lay me in the ballance, I finde moſt others to preponderate; ſith I muſt on the generall audit of my ſelfe, confeſſedly, with Paul, bring in my account with<note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.11 <hi>I am nothing.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and with good <hi>Calvin,</hi> mine empty<note n="k" place="margin">Calvin. Inſt. lib. 2. cap 5. ſect. 13. in fine.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaying of all my beſt parts, and performances, as S. <hi>Andrew</hi> of the five loaves and two fiſhes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; alas!<note n="l" place="margin">John 6.9.</note> What are theſe? They reach not, as I reade of <hi>Davids</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1079:3"/> later Worthies, unto the dignity of the<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 23.19.</note> former, who did not more outſtrip in worth, then <hi>Saul</hi> did overgrow in<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 9.2.</note> ſtature his under brethren, or <hi>Zache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> [<note n="o" place="margin">Luke 19.4.</note> climb'd] up on the Sycamore, o'relooke the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in the way below with Chriſt: But when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I meditate, that even a paire of<note n="p" place="margin">Luke 2.24.</note> Turtles, and the two<note n="q" place="margin">Mar. 12.42, 43.</note> Mites, where there was no more to give, were valued by that God (who meaſureth more by quality, then by<note n="a" place="margin">Non de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonio, ſed de animo opus ejus exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans, &amp; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derans non quantum ſed ex quanto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet. <hi>S. Cypr. lib. de opere &amp; cleemoſyn. ſect.</hi> 14.</note> quantity) as a rich oblation, and a large additament to the common corban, and the treaſurie of the Church; and when I think that my little light, though but as a candle, or a glimmering ray of that orient<note n="b" place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> Sun of righteouſneſſe, is given, and derived to me, not to be hidden under the<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 5.15.</note> buſhell whether of covetouſneſſe, or obſcurity, nor to be ſet under the<note n="d" place="margin">Luke 8.16.</note> bed of lazineſſe, or ſluggiſh eaſe, much leſſe to be dipped in the liquour of what is [<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 5.20.</note> called] good, but
[is] the worſt of fellowſhip, till it be quite extinct; but as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith even of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneſt gift of the Spirit, that its beſtowed, not for oſtentation of the haver, but for to<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.7.</note> profit withall the whole Church; Why ſhould I be ſhie to pay, though but my<note n="g" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.7.</note> rivulet, as in tribute to this Ocean; and to improve, though but my (one) talent, to the beſt advantage of my Lord and Maſter Chriſt, who
<pb facs="tcp:1079:4"/> is wont to give to him that<note n="h" place="margin">Luke 8.18.</note> hath (and having doth employ) the<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 25.28.</note> more, by how much more the good al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie given ſpreadeth, and doth become diffuſive to communitie. I would not therefore with the Spider weave this web to thruſt it to a corner, but with the Silk-worme rather ſpinne my thread ſo that it might help to cloath at leaſt ſome younger children of the Church. I muſt confeſſe the Preſſe may now well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſurfet, and as<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 49.14.</note> 
               <hi>Iſſachar</hi> to couch down under the burdens of thoſe ſons of <hi>Anak,</hi> thoſe Giant-like voluminous writers on this my ſubject: thoſe are your bulky Elephants that with whole<note n="l" place="margin">1 Mac. 6.37.</note> castles-full of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per on their backes, occaſion the common Readers to keep aloofe; their purſe-ſtrings are too weake to tye and hold them, and the acies of their eie-ſight hebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by ſo too-big objects: I have not written<note n="m" place="margin">—Tenuis mihi campus aratur.</note> ſuch Iliades after <hi>Homer:</hi> Many before me have done worthily this<note n="*" place="margin">Eſt illud mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae fertilitatis opus, <hi>Ovid. Triſt. lib. 2.</hi>
               </note> larger way in Ephratah, and for it are become, as the people in the gates told <hi>Boaz,</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note n="n" place="margin">Ruth 4.11.</note> famous in our Bethleem. I have choſen to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent my Mother-Church, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> did <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius,</hi> with an enchiridion onely, as having lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out what is more copiouſly pourtraied by others, into a ſmaller draught, and ſo doe offer it, as were <hi>Homers</hi> Iliades to that mightie Monarch, in a
<pb facs="tcp:1079:4"/> Nutſhell to her. I muſt expect (having thus hoiſed up my ſaile to ſteare amaine) ſome ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſome whiſtlings of your windy ſpirits, that like to ſummer flies will blow corruption on the ſweeteſt of proviſion: Wee are fallen into thoſe times wherein all Sermons are moſt ſure of cenſure, moſt of all unſure of practice; ſo that when our Sermon is ended, wee can hardly ſay our Sermon is done; wee heare more often of our owne good voices, elocution, memorie, then of our hearers holy doings: My hope is not ſo high as to pleaſe all, nor my intention ſo factiouſly ſordid, as to diſpleaſe any; yet I cannot but ſuſpect the worſt, for that whereas I hitherto (mine<note n="o" place="margin">Anno
[tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsimo] car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis aſſumptae, Salvator ad ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gna, &amp; miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, &amp; doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam uſus eſt poteſtate— non antea, quia hac aetate tempus doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae inſinuatum eſt rationabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le; &amp; ante has metas perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram invadi magiſterium data eſt forma; quia non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit annis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pubibus ſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in cathedra, &amp;c. <hi>Cypr. de je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jun. &amp; tentat. Chriſti, Sect.</hi> 1.</note> age not daring farther) have beene one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a Standing in a Faire ſet up before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers doore, and have beene read but in a Preface to ſome bookes publiſhed of my fathers by me; I muſt now ſtand alone upon my owne bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome by my ſelfe: and yet not all alone, but as the learners hand, though framing characters, yet by direction of the Scrivener that holds and guides it, ſo I have ſingly vented nothing, or at all ſteared the leaſt point farther then as I have beene gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the proper ſtarres and cynoſure of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt
<pb facs="tcp:1079:5"/> in our Church of England; whoſe names are now all noted in my margin, which I could not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in my preaching, lest I ſhould have loſt my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in ſo large quotations. Honoured Sir, amidſt the many dangers it is like to meete with, vouchſafe to patronize this my firſt publick Theologicall Eſſay by your countenancing of it: I ſhall [ſo] leſſe feare either the ſpleen or gall of any Reader. One <hi>Plato,</hi> ſaith<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Marcil. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin. in vita Platonis.</hi> Unus Plato plus eſt quàm Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis populus.</note> 
               <hi>Marcilius,</hi> is worth all Athens elſe; one pearle out-vies a thouſand pebles; one ſuch <hi>Mecoenas,</hi> ſo acute an <hi>Ariſtarchus</hi> of all learning (who approves) beares down before him, like an Indian Hurraca, all the ſullen oppoſition of the whole droves of Momus.</p>
            <p>Should I here take occaſion to blazon your ſo many excellent graces, which be like the Spouſes flock of ſheep which came up from the waſhing, even-ſhorne, each one being, not like the Pelican in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, alone, but every one bearing<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.2.</note> twinnes, and none is barren among them: Should I pen-down in this Epiſtle that thoſe which are in others rare, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, are in you but ordinarie and common, I ſhould but make that legible by your owne, which hath long ſince been viſible to the eies of others that have truly known you. But though your various graces (as being all links of one and the ſame chain) might well claime
<pb facs="tcp:1079:5"/> as thoſe in the<note n="b" place="margin">Scholiaſt. in Thucyd.</note> Lacedaemonian army, a priviledge all of them to be Captaines, and to lead; yet that which is, as Davids Tachmonite, the<note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.8.</note> chiefe among theſe Captaines, and which, as King <hi>Lemuels</hi> vertuous daughter, doth<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.29.</note> excell the reſt, is your humble and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired Patience: This is that bulwarke which as a<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.25.</note> rocke returnes the billowes of malevolence in froth, and makes the ſhafts of the meagreſt envie to bee ſplit in vaine: This is that which doth, and ſhall preſerve you, as <hi>Alpheus,</hi> ſtill untainted by the waſhings of the bittereſt<note n="f" place="margin">Sic tibi cùm fluctus ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labêre Sica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Doris amara ſuam non intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat undam. <hi>Virg. Eclog.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Doris,</hi> till you ſalute at laſt the limpid <hi>Arethuſa,</hi> and ſweet fountaine of all bliſſe. I will aſſure you, noble Sir, as the great Doctour of the Gentiles told his endeared Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, my heart is much<note n="g" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note> enlarged towards you, and my reſpectfull thoughts be moſt voluminous, though now my quill (much like mine oratorie, too jejune and dry) hath thus epitomized my expreſsions in a line or two.</p>
            <p>But I perceive, as Jordan above his bankes, the meaſure of my affection hath over-ſwoln the bounds of an Epiſtle: What remaines now, but that I muſt implore the favours of Heaven on you, and that you may ſtill perſiſt to beautifie the ſeat you ſit in, to credit the Weſt, and to adorne the Gospell: Mee,
<pb facs="tcp:1079:6"/> both your ſelfe, and your ſo rarely vertuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, (a genuine branch of a most holy, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout ſtocke) ſhall ever have, though your meanest friend, yet one that hath reſolved to print himſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt true honourer, in my faithfull obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances much devoted, WILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
               <dateline>Exon.
<date>May <hi>11. 1639.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1079:6"/>
            <head>THE WORTHY COMMUNICANT REWARDED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOHN 6.54.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Who ſo eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him up at the last day.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER ſome agitation of thoughts, what moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely I might this day entertaine your noble audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence withall, at length I fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened on this Text; which is that ſacred Map, in which we have compendiated the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1079:7"/> ſumme of thoſe choice favours from above, that now this gladſome anniverſary of our Saviours all-glorious Reſurrection hath oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned to his Church: For now we have more ſolemnly, and more generally renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Covenant with our God, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Seale of all our pardons in the bleſſed Sacrament: Now alſo hath the all-powerfull ariſing of our Head Chriſt Jeſus, carrying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in triumph (as<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 16.3.</note> 
               <hi>Samſon</hi> did the gates of Azzah on his ſhoulders) the bars of Death, Hell, and the Grave (and all this to [aſſure] his members of their complete<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25.</note> juſtification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his offended Father, yea, of their ſure poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of eternall bliſſe) offered it ſelfe unto our meditations. We are (too many of us) as Chriſt ſaid unto the two Diſciples, (whereof the one was named <hi>Cleophas,</hi> and the other one <hi>Ammaon,</hi> as St. <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> or <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanael,</hi> as<note n="c" place="margin">Epiphan. haer. <hi>23.</hi> ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> or elſe S. <hi>Luke</hi> himſelf, the Writer of the ſtory, as <hi>Haymo, Lyranus,</hi> and <hi>Theophylact</hi> opine) to theſe two (what ever was the others name) going to Emmaus; we are, I ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.25.</note> 
               <hi>ſlow of heart</hi> to beleeve, at leaſt wiſe, through want of a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1079:7"/> more earneſt taking-heed unto the things we heare; ſo ſieve-like are our memories, that they doe<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as St. <hi>Pauls</hi> word is, let ſlip, and to run out as leaking veſſels, what ſhould better be retained. Wherefore as the Manna, on the Jewiſh Sabbath, being<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.24</note> laid up in a pot, was rendred ſweet and freſh for uſe; ſo, that we may not, as ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iſrael, ſo ſoone<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 106.13</note> forget the wonders of the Lord, ſo marvellous in our eyes, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the contrary; as Ophir, in the dayes of <hi>Solomon,</hi> was the place for gold, becauſe the moſt and beſt was there; ſo went I for a ſeaſonable Text herefore, to this golden and beaten chapter (as well travelled in this kind, as Ophir was for gold) becauſe here was the richeſt veine to furniſh ſuch an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: thence have I extracted a ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell for my building, the two chiefe Pillars of which building, as<note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz</hi> in <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, are the two maine Articles of our Chriſtian faith, <hi>viz.</hi> the reſurrection of the dead, and the life everlaſting: And that which, as <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt did to Chriſt, fore-runneth, and<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.3.</note> prepares the way to ſolid
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1079:8"/> comfort in them both, is, to eat the fleſh, and to drinke the bloud of Chriſt; whoſe fleſh is meat indeed, and whoſe bloud is drinke indeed, verſe 55. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> [indeed] becauſe no food in ſhadow, or in type, but truely, and in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; [indeed] becauſe not provant for the body, but ſpirituall nouriſhment of the ſoul; [indeed] becauſe not<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.22.</note> periſhing with the uſing, but an heavenly viond, a food<note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.8</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending us to God, and nouriſhing up for ever unto life eternall: Theſe four then, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">The diviſion.</note>1. The manducation of the fleſh of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. The compotation of the bloud of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>3. The reſurrection of the body: And laſtly,</item>
                  <item>4. The poſſeſsion of eternall life; the certain iſſue of the other three.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe foure, like the foure rivers in the garden of<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.10.</note> Eden, doe all ſpring from the pure fountaine of this Scripture, and muſt now flow abroad into ſo many ſeverall ſtreames of diſcourſe, which in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſpreading ſhall make glad, I hope, this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1079:8"/> City of God: The ſame hand that gave the opportunity, vouchſafe to give ſucceſſe to this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſo eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him up at the last day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall begin in that<note n="n" place="margin">Singula quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> locum teneant <hi>dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> decenter. <hi>Horat. de Arte Poetica.</hi>
               </note> order which the Text preſenteth the parts in, and in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer generalls obſerve, 1. The gueſt invited to this heavenly Feaſt [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Whoſo,</hi> or, as the Genevians render it, <hi>Whoſoever,</hi> anſwering to that [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] in Saint<note n="o" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27</note> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> the parallel Scripture unto this, 1 Cor. 11.27. 2. The proviſion made to entertaine theſe gueſts, the fleſh and bloud of Chriſt, for meat and drink. 3. The two actions, with their relation to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall object, [eating] the fleſh, and [drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king] the bloud of Chriſt. 4. And fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the conjunction of both theſe together (for which cauſe I called it a compotation) not fleſh onely without bloud, but bloud alſo as equally as the fleſh; and both reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively to the [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] in the beginning. Of theſe in their order.</p>
            <p>This <hi>[Whoſo]</hi> is not either ſo univerſall,<note place="margin">The firſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:1079:9"/> or indefinite, that <hi>pell mell</hi> promiſcuouſly, by vertue of [it] all commers, or intruders were to be admitted to this ſacred ſoules-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt, (though it be true, that every worthy and accompliſhed gueſt may take [<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1.2.</note> freely] of the heavenly Supper, and without coſt; Come, ſaith the Prophet, eat ye that which is good, and let your ſoule delight it ſelfe in fatneſſe, and all without money, and without price, Iſa. 55.1.2.) — <hi>Procul hinc, procul ite profani:</hi> For if he that thruſt himſelfe in without his<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.11.13.</note> wedding garment to the Kings Feaſt, was ſhamefully bound hand and foot, and caſt into outer darkneſſe, where there was weeping and gnaſhing of teeth; if there bee a <hi>Nolite ſanctum canibus,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6.</note> holy things, and pearles be interdicted unto dogges, and ſwine, unto perſons of a curriſh, and ſwiniſh diſpoſition, that ſtill, as<note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, are turning backe to their vomit, and to their wallowing in the mire of all impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency:—Was a beaſt ſlain for touching the<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.20.</note> mount? and ſhall not a perſon that is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brutiſhed, and ſunke below his <hi>ſpecies</hi> in vile affections, bee puniſhed for touching that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1079:9"/> Table, where the Lord is preſent? Loe! He that eates Chriſts fleſh with a foule mouth, and receives him into an uncleanſed and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule, doth (as one ſaith well) all one, as if he ſhould ſop the bread he eates in dirt, or lay up his richeſt treaſures in a ſinke: No ſuch unworthy and undreſſed gueſts are to touch here; yea, if they ſhould, all that they eat or drinke, is but ſure<note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29</note> judgement, and damnation to themſelves, by ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous impreparation laying themſelves open to the ſtrokes of Gods diſpleaſure; of which <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> in a parallel caſe, are exampled out for our warning, being ſuddenly deſtroyed for offering<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.2.</note> ſtrange fire at Gods Altar: and no leſſe are thoſe endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that preſent ſtrange ſouls, and a falſe faith at Chriſts Table; for ſurely, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> God wil be<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 3.</note> ſanctified in them that come nigh him: Wherefore our Saviour, whoſe eſſence was Purity it ſelf <hi>in abſtracto,</hi> when he meant, though not to lay downe any thing w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he had before, to wit, his Divinity (ſave only, as<note n="f" place="margin">Pantolcon, tract. de lumin. ſanct. pag. <hi>587.</hi> in patrum <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Pantoleon</hi> hath it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1079:10"/> act, and time of his exinanition, he ſeemed awhiles to ſhadow the manifeſtation, and as it were to hide the glorious ſplendour of the ſame) yet to aſſume unto his divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon another Nature, and that not of Angels, for [ſome] of them ſtood, but of Man, whoſe [whole] <hi>ſpecies</hi> was quite loſt, as ſay the School-men, in the fall of <hi>Adam:</hi> In this his incarnation, or aſſumption of his humanity, he choſe the wombe of none but of a pure Virgin to be lodged in; for as no uncleane thing can enter into the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, no more would the King of Heaven enter into any uncleane thing: hee was a Lamb without<note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</note> ſpot, or blemiſh, and could not therefore enter into a leprous ſoule; yea, his very body, and his fleſh ſo pure, that thoſe two noble Converts of his, <hi>Joſeph</hi> of Arimathea, and his<note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.50.</note> night-Diſciple <hi>Nicodemus</hi> thought it fitteſt, as <hi>Primaſius</hi> noteth out of St. <hi>John,</hi> to be wound up onely in [linnen] cloaths, and with ſweet ſpices and fragrant odours, to be interred in a [new] ſepulchre, never ſoyled by a ſinfull body, Joh. 19.40, 41. And when himſelfe was now about to give
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1079:10"/> this ſame body of his in Sacrament, at the firſt inſtitution of his laſt bleſſed Supper, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Diſciples, its noted by the ſame Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, chap. 13.4, 5. that he riſeth from ſupper, that is, if I miſconceive not, from the ſecond and common ſupper (now begun) next to the eating of the Paſſeover, which was the firſt and legall ſupper, which the word [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] riſing up, partly intimates: For the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Paſſeover, as we may gather from Exod. 12.11. was to be eaten [ſtanding] with ſtaves in their hands; and at which [common] ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per it was, before it was wholly ended, that <hi>Judas</hi> eate the ſop, and had his traiterous hand with his Maſter in the diſh: after which ſop (no Sacramentall ſop, as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, with a<note n="n" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Kellet Canon Reſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiary in his book entituled, <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coenium Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> not more full of ſoliditie, then curioſity of all great learning: now pregnant, and ready to be delivered from a well-furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Librarie into publike.</note> learned Profeſſor of Divinity a member of this Church) immediately he went out, Ver. 30. to doe that work of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for to ſerve his trueſt Maſter the Prince of Darkneſſe, in betraying the<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.4.</note> innocent bloud of the Prince of light, into the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therous hands of the Children of Darkneſſe: He went out, and it was Night, that is, ſaith
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1079:11"/> 
               <hi>Alcuinus,</hi> He, <hi>Judas</hi> himſelfe, was ſo perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and <hi>in abſtracto,</hi> he had a ſoule within ſo foule and blacke with this deed of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: I ſay, from this ſecond and common ſupper (thus begun) and before the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the third, and laſt holy ſupper, which was not till after he ſate downe again, upon the ablution of his Diſciples feet, and after too, that <hi>Judas</hi> was gone out for to betray him; which<note n="p" place="margin">Beza ad Joh. <hi>13.20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> noteth from the adverb [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] ver. 30. [Immediately] hee went forth, that is, immediately after the ſop, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the diſh in that common ſupper, (for where is the Sacramentall bread called a ſop?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.26.</note> or at leaſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a [dipped] ſop, as this is ſaid to be, ver. 26?) I ſay, once more, from this ſecond, and this common ſupper Jeſus riſeth, and laid aſide his garments, and took a towell, and girded himſelfe; after that, he poureth water into a baſon, and began to waſh the Diſciples feet, and to wipe them with the towell wherewith he was girded. The maine paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in this Scripture that I mind for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe, is the [waſhing of the Diſciples
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1079:11"/> feet]: and yet becauſe we cannot baulk that Theological Maxime here, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſaith, that <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Chriſti actio noſtra eſt inſtructio,</hi> Every action of Chriſt (onely thoſe excepted which were of<note n="r" place="margin">Nos non te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemur Deum imitari in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus [poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis] imò tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur velle non imitari ipſum, quia debemus ei velle ſoli omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam. <hi>Vide Alex. Hales par.</hi> 4. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 33. <hi>mem.</hi> 1. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 827. <hi>edit.</hi> 1622.</note> miraculous and extraordinary diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which by vertue of the union hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall were done alone by him, in which we cannot, nor ought to ſtrive to reſemble) is our inſtruction, and calls for our obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and imitation, at leaſt, <hi>quantum ad ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam actus,</hi> though not to be hoped, or attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by us, <hi>quantum ad agendi modum,</hi> as<note n="ſ" place="margin">Alex. Hales, par. <hi>4</hi> qu. <hi>10.</hi> p. <hi>298.</hi> edit. <hi>1622.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Hales</hi> diſtinguiſheth: that is, for the ſubſtance, though not the full manner, or meaſure of exact performance of the action; (for what compariſon?) Therefore I will firſt a little touch upon the depending<note n="t" place="margin">Solet [cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantia] Scripturae il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminare ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam, cùm ea quae circa Scripturam ſunt praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem quaeſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genti diſcuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one tractan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Auguſt. qu.</hi> 69. <hi>l. de diverſ. quaeſt. —Confer Primaſium in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 15. <hi>p.</hi> 229 <hi>in</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances: Firſt then, he riſing from the ſecond ſupper
[laid aſide his garments.] For the better underſtanding of the myſtery here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we may remember, that the Scripture mentions a threefold glorious garment, that the Lord puts on, as the King of glory, to whom the everlaſting<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.7.</note> doores ſtand open.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1079:12"/> 1. The firſt is a garment of ſtrength, Pſal. 93.1. The Lord raigneth, he is cloathed with Majeſty, hee is cloathed with [ſtrength] wherewith he hath girded himſelfe. 2. The ſecond is a garment of honour, and beauty, Pſal. 104.1. Thou art cloathed with [ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour] and Majeſty. 3. A third is the garment of light; Who covereſt thy ſelfe with [light] as with a garment, Pſal. 104.2. All theſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments our Saviour laid aſide, when he roſe up, and came downe from heaven, and put on our<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</note> vile fleſh upon him, (not indeed as ever loſing his firſt glory, but under the vaile of our nature covering the manifeſtation thereof) by that meanes becomming, as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> hath it, <hi>Deus abſconditus,</hi> a God that<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.15.</note> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe; for in ſtead of ſtrength, of beauty, and of light, loe! the three contrary weeds of infirmity, of humility, of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; He emptied, he<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7, 8.</note> humbled himſelf, ſaith the Apoſtle; he hath no forme, nor comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and when wee ſhall ſee him, there is no beauty that we ſhould deſire him, a man of ſorrowes, and we hid, as it were, our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from him; He was deſpiſed, and wee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1079:12"/> eſteemed him not, Iſa. 53.2, 3. So were all his [glorious] garments laid by, repreſented now by his laying aſide of theſe. 2. Having laid aſide his garments, he next took a towel, and girded himſelfe, being ſo found in the form of a ſervant, and in<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8.</note> faſhion of a man, that came not to be miniſtred unto, but to<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28.</note> miniſter. 3. After this, he poureth water into a baſon; hereby ſignifying, partly, the cooling of the heat of concupiſcence, by the<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25.</note> water of his grace in the hearts of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, as<note n="g" place="margin">Perer. diſput. <hi>15.</hi> ad cap. <hi>13.</hi> Johan.</note> 
               <hi>Pererius;</hi> and partly ſhewing, as<note n="h" place="margin">Ludolph. de Saxon. part. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>54.</hi> de vita Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>Ludolphus</hi> out of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, how now ſhortly he would poure out his bloud, and ſhed it on the ground, for the abſterſion and cleanſing of their ſoules from the filthineſſe of ſin, 1 Joh. 1.7. 4. All this done, Then he began [to waſh the Diſciples feet;] by which action he firſt ſhewed the depth of his abjection, and likeneſſe even unto the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſervant upon earth: therefore when humble and diſcreet <hi>Abigail</hi> would abaſe her ſelf even unto the meaneſt offices, as<note n="k" place="margin">Pet. Martyr. loc. commun. claſſ. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> ſect. <hi>15.</hi> p. <hi>887.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr</hi> hath well noted, as thinking her ſelfe unworthy of any higher, in <hi>Davids</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:1079:13"/> Court, ſhe ſaith, Let thine handmaid be a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to [waſh the feet] of the ſervants of my Lord, 1 Sam. 25.41. Set theſe two together, The King of glory, the ſhame of men; the<note n="m" place="margin">My Lord Joſ. Hall the now peerleſſe Biſhop of Exon. Paſsion Serm. p. <hi>505.</hi> edit. <hi>1617.</hi>
               </note> more honour, the more abaſement: In the third verſe, St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith of our Saviour, He came from God, and went to God; Loe! what a diſparity is here; by Nature, God cloathed with Majeſty, and eternall glory,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6.</note> equall to God the Father, conſubſtantiall with the holy Ghoſt, now a ſervant, and employed in the loweſt offices of the vileſt ſervant: Who muſt not here cry out with the Prophet,<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.8.</note> O drop downe righteouſneſſe ye Heavens, and let the earth be aſtoniſhed at this? And in the uſe, thus muſt we apply it: When we addreſſe our ſelves to eat that ſupper, which now was, in this faſhion, about to be inſtituted by Chriſt, we muſt lay by all thoughts of honour, of place, of all kind of ſelfe-worthineſſe, if we minde to eat with profit.<note n="p" place="margin">Sulpit. Sever. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sulpitius</hi> much magnifieth the humility of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> for that he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times miniſtred unto his owne ſervant; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that <hi>Lewis</hi> King of France, who was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1079:13"/> wont to ſerve the poore with his owne hands; which thing likewiſe<note n="q" place="margin">Niceph. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nicephorus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth of <hi>Helena</hi> the mother of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great; and<note n="r" place="margin">Platin. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Leonis noni p. <hi>171.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Platina</hi> noteth it as a high point of piety in Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Leper lying before his doore, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to bee layed in his owne bed: But alas! as St. <hi>Andrew</hi> ſaid of the five loaves, and two fiſhes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Alas!<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.9.</note> what are theſe? when loe! the God of glory humbleth himſelfe, as 'twere unto the very duſt of ſcorne, of contempt, of ſhame; He refuſeth not to waſh even the very feet of his Diſciples: But yet there is a farther myſtery in this, which I gather from Joh. 13.10. where our Saviour tells <hi>Peter,</hi> He that is waſhed needeth not ſave to waſh his [feet,] for by this action of his was not meant onely, in the letter, his conforming of himſelfe unto a Jewiſh cuſtome, who in thoſe hotter climates went diſcalceated, and without ſhooes, at leaſt<note n="o" place="margin">See the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva note, at Joh. <hi>13.23.</hi>
               </note> leaned ſo at their meales; but, in the myſtery, becauſe done at this [time] as the ancients obſerve, it deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the abſterſion, and waſhing away, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1079:14"/> ſhould be in us, by the waters of teares, and repentance, from the inward affections, which be as the feet of the ſoule, of that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant pollution, that as <hi>Shechems</hi> ſoule did in a luxurious love to <hi>Dinah, Jacobs</hi> daughter, doth [<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.3.</note> cleave] too cloſe unto them; ſo St.<note n="y" place="margin">Bern. fol. <hi>35.</hi> F. in ſerm. de Coena Dom.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> moſt expreſly: ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily then thus, ſith as that noble Lord<note n="a" place="margin">Du Pleſsis, cap. <hi>30.</hi> de vera Relig. in fronte.</note> 
               <hi>Du Pleſsis</hi> tells us, that <hi>Chriſti tota vita ſalutis ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> Chriſts whole life was but the Schoole from whence we muſt take out the leſſons of our practice, and our Saviour himſelfe, after theſe things thus done, ſaith ver. 15. I have given you an<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.15.</note> example, that ye ſhould doe, as I have done unto you; by laying aſide his garments, tutoureth us to put off the<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21.</note> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities of naughtineſſe, our<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6.</note> menſtruous ragges, our<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude</hi> 23.</note> garments ſpotted of the fleſh, and with <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> caſt<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.50.</note> away our ſinfull garments, when we riſe up, and come to Chriſt; by girding of himſelfe with a tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, which had a reſpective correſpondency to the poſture wherein the Jewiſh Paſſeover was eaten, to wit, with their<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.11.</note> loynes girded, to<note n="g" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.35.</note> gird up the loynes of our mindes, by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1079:14"/> curbing of our luxury, and laſcivious exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies; and by waſhing of the feet, to teach us to<note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</note> rinſe, and ſcoure our affections from all naſty defilements, that doe beſpot and beſweat the ſoule, rendring it loathſom to the eyes of the<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13.</note> all-pure God: which was alſo typed in thoſe<note n="k" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.6.</note> lavers ſet before the Temple, wherein the Prieſt was firſt to waſh, before he entred: And to what end ſerved all thoſe Leviticall Purifications in the myſtery, but to this ſame purpoſe? The <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies</hi> indeed of the ceremony lay in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waſhings, but the morall intelligence, as the Schoole calls it, eyed the inward rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the ſoule, and<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</note> conſcience from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full impurity; and for this cauſe alſo ſome have thought that amongſt other wood the Lord choſe out unto himſelf for an offering,<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.5.</note> Shittim wood, and thereof enjoyned the<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10.</note> Ark to be made up; <hi>Ligna Sethim ſunt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vide Pet. Lumbard. l <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>8</hi> in ſinc.</note> 
               <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putribilia,</hi> for that its thought to be a kind of Cedar, that admits not eaſily of a rotting; no more muſt any ſoule allow himſelfe in any ſinne, that in the iſſue ſokes, and rotteth out the ſoule: Chriſt owneth no ſuch moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1079:15"/> gueſts, nor bids them well-come at his Table.</p>
            <p>Wherefore this [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] or, <hi>Whoſo,</hi> or, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,</hi> do here ſtand as <hi>Abraham</hi> in his Tent, in the<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.1.</note> doore of this Text, ſeeming to invite all paſſengers, and to call in all commers to this heavenly repaſt upon the fleſh and bloud of Chriſt; yet this muſt be reſtrained onely unto ſuch as be found<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.8.</note> worthy, and, as the five wiſe virgins, have their lampes all<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.7.10.</note> ready-trimmed, and prepared for admiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I could here take occaſion to reckon up thoſe fifteene kinds of perſons, which (du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their ill-diſpoſed ſtate) are excluded by the<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Rayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium de Piſis, tom. <hi>1.</hi> Pantheo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. cap. <hi>17.</hi> in Euchariſtia.</note> Schoole-Divines; but I would gladly keep my ſelfe unto the rubrick of my houre.</p>
            <p>Its true, what<note n="a" place="margin">Granatenſis, tom. <hi>2.</hi> concio de Temp. concio <hi>4.</hi> in coena Dom.</note> 
               <hi>Granatenſis</hi> here obſerves, that the worthineſſe notwithſtanding of theſe gueſts of Chriſt, is not to be meaſured by the nobility of deſcent, nor ignobility of condition, neither by pompe, nor poverty from without: Our King Chriſt Jeſus hath a Kingdome indeed, but its not of this<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.36.</note> world; therefore the dignity of his gueſts is to be meaſured, as the Kings daughter in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1079:15"/> the Pſalme, by what nobility they have [<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 45.13.</note> within,] by what luſtre of graces their ſoules are adorned with [there:] if they have<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22.</note> ſingle eyes, that is, mindes clearly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with knowledge, enough to<note n="e" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29</note> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern the Lords body from ordinary refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; elſe, as<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.46.</note> 
               <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> they are deformed in their ſight: if they have cleanſed affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; elſe, they are as <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.4.</note> lame in their feet: if they have<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29.</note> edifying diſcourſe; elſe, as that Stutterer in the Goſpel, they have an<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.32.35.</note> impediment in their ſpeech, and the ſtrings muſt firſt be looſed: if they be ready to<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13.</note> diſtribute; elſe, as <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> they bee<note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 13.4.</note> ſhrunke up in their hands: if free from all ſinnes mortall, wounding and waſting the conſcience; elſe, as thoſe Lameſters at the poole of<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Betheſda,</hi> they are too ulcerous, and full of ſores, to be entertained by this King: Go, ſaith the Lord by <hi>Malachi,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.8, 13, 14.</note> offer the lame, and the ſicke, and the torne, offer theſe unto thy Governour, will he be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with thee, or accept thy perſon? Loe! thus it is, when wee come with maimed ſoules, we pollute the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Table of the Lord,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1079:16"/> we cannot be accepted at his ſacred boord. Wherefore, to cloſe up this point, let me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you all, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth his<note n="o" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28</note> Corinthians, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let every particular man examine himſelfe, and, as the word imports, put himſelf upon the tryall. Examination is the eye of the ſoul, by which reflexively it ſeeth it ſelfe, and knoweth what it hath done: Other meates, ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> are, e're they be taken, to be firſt proved, leſt they hurt us; but here, leſt this heavenly meat prove noxious to thee, thou muſt firſt goe prove [thy ſelfe:] Judge<note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31</note> your ſelves therefore, Brethren, that ye be not jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the Lord: let us be impartiall in the ſcrutiny of our hollow, and<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note> deceitfull hearts; and, like the woman that ſought her groat, in the Goſpel, light up the candle of our beſt faculties, and leave no corner of our ſoules<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.8.</note> unſwept, till we have found out that ſin of our ſoules, that doth, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, ſo<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1.</note> eaſily beſet us, and, as that Jebuſite in Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that will not out of our coaſts; and when we have diſcovered it, to<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.</note> mortifie it, and to<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</note> crucifie it, with the affections, and luſts
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1079:16"/> thereof: And as the ſpeciall ſacrifice that was offered upon the Altar in Jeruſalem, was wont diligently to bee looked into by the high Prieſt, and his Miniſters, to ſpy out the blemiſhes, or otherwiſe, of it, before the actuall oblation, ſo let us. S.<note n="e" place="margin">S. Clement. epiſt. ad Cor. pag. <hi>53, 54.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clement</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Corinthians (a late, and<note n="*" place="margin">See M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Mede Serm. of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of Gods houſe, p. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine monument of antiquity ſet forth) hath expreſſed it to the life thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which word is interpreted by<note n="e" place="margin">Philo Judaeus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Philo Judaeus</hi> thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it implyeth ſuch a diſquiſition, ſo exact, as if <hi>Momus</hi> himſelfe with a Lince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an eye, were to come after, hee ſhould not finde a thing to carpe at, in the very entrails of our ſacrifices of our ſoules: The ſame word is uſed by St.<note n="f" place="margin">Chryſ. Hom. <hi>20.</hi> in Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> upon this occaſion of pre-examination, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. Thus we [ſhould] doe from the bottome of our ſoules: wherefore<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4 8.</note> cleanſe your hands you ſinners, and purifie your hearts ye double-minded. Thus if we doe, at leaſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1079:17"/> in<note n="*" place="margin">Tota vita boni Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni eſt ſanctum deſiderium.</note> deſire, and endevour, we then come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this ſame [ὁ] <hi>Whoſo,</hi> in my Text, and are the men, whoſoever we be for externall condition in ſtate or place, that be all invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hither to eat, and to drinke, and that of no meaner cheare then the very fleſh and bloud of Chriſt Jeſus himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And thus I paſſe from the gueſts, unto the proviſion made ready for them, the fleſh and the bloud of Chriſt: [Whoſo] <hi>eateth my</hi> [fleſh] <hi>and drinketh my</hi>
[bloud.]</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Fleſh and bloud! theſe are ſtrange cates to make a banquet of. We read in the Scripture, that<note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50</note> fleſh and bloud cannot enter into the Kingdome of heaven, (but that's meant of fleſh corruption, not of fleſh the ſubſtance, as the words enſuing ſhew; for as there is Iron, ſo the ruſt of Iron) how much leſſe ſhall he that
[feeds] upon it for his food? <hi>Satia te ſanguine, quem ſitiſti,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tamyris,</hi> as I remember, in<note n="i" place="margin">Juſtin. hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Juſtins</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, to <hi>Cyrus,</hi> when his head was off, and caſt into a veſſell full of bloud, Now ſurfet on that bloud which thou ſo much thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtedſt after. It was a law of Gods owne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1079:17"/> He that ſheds<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6.</note> mans bloud, by man alſo ſhall his bloud be ſhed. <hi>My fleſh, and my Bloud!</hi> Surely what the Iſraelites ſaid of Manna, when firſt they ſaw, and taſted it, crying out in admiration,<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.15</note> 
               <hi>Man-hu,</hi> What is this portion, or meat prepared for us? for they wiſt not, ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> what it was; ſo may many a man that knowes not how to diſcerne the Lords Body: ſuch an one is apt to thinke, with that monſter <hi>Cacus</hi> in the Poet, who from his wickedneſſe <hi>in abſtracto,</hi> had his name [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">—Foribuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> affixa ſuperbis ora [virûm] triſti pende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant pallida tabo. <hi>Virg. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Servius,</hi> that nought but<note n="*" place="margin">Servius ib. fol. <hi>505.</hi>
               </note> mans fleſh muſt be drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his den; and as ſome ſavage Cannibal profeſsing anthropophagie, as ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, man-hating <hi>Miſo,</hi> ſome Minotaure, or bloudy<note n="*" place="margin">Sen. Tragaed. in Thyeſte.</note> 
               <hi>Atreus,</hi> or the like prodigies of nature, that man was made to be<note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12.</note> taken, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of brute beaſts, and to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and as the<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 19.</note> Levites concubine, to be chopt in pieces. Thus ſurely may your dull Capernaites, and unilluminated men imagine; for ſo they ſtrove among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſaying, How can this man give us his fleſh to eat? John 6.52. yea more then ſo,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1079:18"/> ver. 60. many, even of Chriſts owne Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, when they heard this, ſaid, <hi>Durus est hic ſenno,</hi> this is a hard ſaying, who can beare it? And the very truth is this, its that which po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth nature utterly, and makes her ſtand, as he without his wedding garment, in the Goſpel, upon conviction,<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.12.</note> ſpeechleſſe.</p>
            <p>But though the words, as they are in the ſhell, be hard to pierce into, yet when as our Saviour hath to our hands broken it for us, we may eaſily take out the kernell of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The main ſcope of the Text.</note>The mind of our Saviour in this Text, which is but repeated from the former ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, is, to ſhew us the ſweet effect of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eating of his body, and drinking of his bloud by faith, above that other orall eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and drinking of the bread and wine, which are but the Sacraments thereof, and may be taken as well by Hypocrites, as by True believers. This myſticall partaking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally procureth eternall life, after the reſurrection, whereas the other, which is meerly outward, and no more, may yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to<note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29</note> judgement, and damnation; the reaſon is, becauſe the one partakes of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1079:18"/> Lord himſelfe, who is the Bread of life, Joh. 6.35. whom to know, and with whom to have communion aright, is life eternall, Joh. 17.3. The other, onely of the bread [of] the Lord, which hath no vertue, without faith, at all, to procure ſuch endleſſe bliſſe: yea more, <hi>Dum Sacramenta poſſunt obeſſe,</hi> as St. <hi>Austin</hi> truly: when thoſe elements of Bread and Wine once conſecrated by the lawfull miniſter, and changed by that act of his, (duely, and as it ought, performed) though not from their<note n="q" place="margin">Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim id Chriſtus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, ut panis friticeus abji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret [natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram] ſuam, ac novam quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam divinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem indueret, ſed ut nos po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, ut<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophylactus lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur (in Joh. 6.) [tranſe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaret] in corpus ſuum. <hi>Juel. Apol. p.</hi> 41 <hi>vol.</hi> 16.</note> nature, yet in their uſe, which is now become no longer<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſt. Mart. Apol. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but holy, and Sacramentall; when, I ſay, they be thus changed in their uſe, then to partake them without faith, endangereth that worthleſſe receiver, as thoſe luſted after quailes did the faithleſſe, and unruly Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, unto a ſpeedy and a ſudden overthrow, even whiles betwixt their<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 11.33</note> teeth: And yet all this too, not through the leaſt defect in Sacraments themſelves, for they have ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude and fitneſſe, in their deſignation natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall, not onely to repreſent, to declare, and ſhew as ſignes, and to confirme as<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</note> Seales,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1079:19"/> but even as ſacred Inſtruments to<note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</note> Save, and as effectuall meanes, though not by vertue of any <hi>opus operatum,</hi> or
[<note n="*" place="margin">See my Lo. Grace, ſect. <hi>33.</hi> p. <hi>271, 272, 273,</hi> &amp;c. &amp; p. <hi>307.</hi> &amp; ſect. <hi>38.</hi> p. <hi>327.</hi> num. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> intention] of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrer, (both which, as <hi>Bel-ſhazzar</hi> in the ballance, may bee found too<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.27.</note> light) yet of Gods owne ordinance, to exhibite, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the very body and bloud of Chriſt unto the right receiver: for they be not empty pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants, or naked ſhewes; not theoricall, but practicall ſignes, though our groſſe Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts would faine perſwade the world that we teach otherwiſe: But all the ill iſſue is in the defect of the good<note n="*" place="margin">Tale cujuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſacrificium, qualis eſt is qui accedit ut ſumat; omnia munda mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis. <hi>Aug l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 52. <hi>cont. Petilian.</hi>
               </note> motion of the Uſer: The better the meat, the worſe the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yea the more dangerous the humours, and the dropſie more deadly, if the liver faile in making of good bloud, occaſioning the body, like ſome mariſh grounds in the midſt of a wateriſh bogge, to ſwell, and the ſpleene to puffe, and not diſperſing proper ſpirits into the veines, which may, as 'twere embroyder the whole body in native, and in azure beauty:<note n="*" place="margin">Horat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sincerum eſt niſi vas, quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque infundis aceſcit,</hi> ſaith the Poet, the beſt wines may ſowre, and become unſavoury,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1079:19"/> if the But bee not rinſed; and the pureſt ſtreames be corrupted through the muddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the channell. Take a ſeale, apply it to a ſtone, it makes no more impreſsion of its owne image, then thoſe afflictions did on <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, which was in judgment<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.35.</note> har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened; but ſtamp it on the wax, the yeelding, melting, faithfull heart, loe! this ſeale of the Sacrament leaves there a Character as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Elect of Chriſt, as was to <hi>Ceſars</hi> coyne the<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.20, 21.</note> image of <hi>Ceſar.</hi> Whence is this difference? not from the Scale, that's ſtill the ſame, but from the ſeverall hearts ſo ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed, that there is no more agreement 'twixt them, then there is 'twixt faith and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, then was between an Egyptian and a Shepheard, betweene Chriſt and Belial; the one, ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> is an<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.34.</note> abomination to the other, and betweene the other two, ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> there is no Communion: certainly its true, <hi>Sacramenta non proſunt ſine bono motu utentis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this is the genuine purpoſe of our Saviour, namely, under this expreſsion of fleſh and bloud, to acquaint us, that the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1079:20"/> proviſion he intends is <hi>Cibus mentis,</hi> and not <hi>Cibus ventris,</hi> is cleare, firſt in the generall, as the<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Centur.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 125. <hi>edit.</hi> 1624.</note> 
               <hi>Magdeburgenſes</hi> have obſerved, from that reply of Chriſt to his Diſciples, to whom this ſaying was ſo hard, ver. 63. <hi>It is the Spirit that quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing; the words that I ſpeake unto you, they are ſpirit, and they are life;</hi> not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as Capernaites apprehended it, in a groſſe and carnall meaning; as likewiſe by thoſe many equipollent phraſes, tending all of them to expreſſe the ſame thing, in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſes: for that which he, in my Text, calleth [fleſh and bloud] in the 51. verſe, he calleth the living [bread] which came downe from heaven; and, if any man eat of this [bread] he ſhall live for ever, and, the [bread] that I will give, is my [fleſh,] that is, my fleſh ſhall be [as] bread, to nouriſh the ſoule unto life eternall, even as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread doth ſerve to feed the body unto this life corporall: and that the [eating and drinking] is alſo ſpirituall, and of faith, is evident out of ver. 40. where the ſame effect that is here aſcribed to eating, and drinking,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1079:20"/> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> eternal life, is given unto [beleeving:] ſo that theſe tropical ſpeeches, rightly take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are converti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for in this variety of expreſsion, Chriſt doth but tranſpoſe the propoſition, as<note n="l" place="margin">Pet. Martyr. loc. com. claſſ. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> ſect. <hi>34.</hi> p. <hi>856.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>P. Martyr</hi> notes; for as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 51.</note> before, he ſaid, <hi>that the bread that I will give is my fleſh;</hi> ſo in the text, his fleſh having
[eating] adjoyned to it, is in ſtead of bread, and in equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollency the very ſame, <hi>ut<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> corpore editis pane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ita mente veſcamini carne meâ.</hi> And to clear it yet a litle more, conſider we, in the buſineſs of the ſupper, two things, the outward &amp; viſible part, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Schools call properly <hi>Sacramentum</hi> (in a more ſtrict acception of the word) and that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp; inviſible, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they term <hi>rem Sacramenti,</hi> the principal thing exhibited in the Sacrament. Thus in the Lords ſupper, the ſacrament is bread and wine, &amp; in the outward part of this myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call action, we receive this body and bloud but ſacramentally; the inward thing, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend by faith, is, the body and bloud of Chriſt; and in the inward part of this myſticall action, which contains <hi>rem,</hi> we receive them really, and conſequently, the preſence in the one is Relative and ſymbolical, in the other, Reall &amp; ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; as that great light of the Church, the deeply-learned
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1079:21"/> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">My Lord Archbiſhop Usſher Serm. on <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>10.17.</hi> pag. <hi>13.</hi> vol. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Primate of Armagh, hath ſhewen us.</p>
            <p>And now, would all good moderate Chriſtians, baulking your wrangling Iſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, being more ſhye of all that baggage which the School-men ſoile Divinity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, out of the Philoſophers puddles, and their own, (as<note n="m" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds,</hi> p. <hi>652.</hi> concluſ. <hi>5.</hi> added to the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with <hi>Hart.</hi>
               </note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Raynolds</hi> truly ſpeaketh;) would they poyſe their judgements at this ballance of the Sanctuary, and pray for the illumination of that Spirit, whoſe grace in the operation, is compared to<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11.</note> fire, by <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, the nature of which fire is, both <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregare homogenea, &amp; ſegregare heterogenea,</hi> (as in Philoſophy we uſe to ſpeak) both to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne thoſe things that be of the ſame, and to diſ-joyne ſuch as be of a differing kinde, and diſpoſition; would they ſet faith to feed ſpiritually upon the very fleſh and bloud of Chriſt, whoſe phyſicall, and naturall body is perſonally in the eternall word, locally in<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21.</note> Heaven onely (the firſt that taught other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and brought in the locall preſence, even ſtill on earth, was <hi>Scotus,</hi> whom <hi>Occam</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and both but of yeſterday, as our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1079:21"/> worthy<note n="o" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Field</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi> in append.</note> 
               <hi>Field</hi> hath ſhewen us) Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally in the Euchariſt, and<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</note> alwayes with the Elect ſpiritually in the ſoule: and on the other ſide, ſet their bodily mouths to feed upon the outward viſible bread, but yet as cloathed too with a Sacramentall relation to the fleſh of Chriſt, ſymbolically ſigned thereby: And ſecondly, if they would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low learned<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hooker</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> Eccleſ. pol. p. <hi>357.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hookers</hi> counſell, a worthy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in our Church, who wiſhed that men would more give themſelves to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate with ſilence [what] wee have by the Sacrament, and leſſe to diſpute of the [man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner] (how,) at leaſt conſidering that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe which Truth hath hitherto had by ſo bitter conflicts with errour in this point: Thus if we could be perſwaded, oh what honey might we ſucke as<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 14.9.</note> 
               <hi>Samſon</hi> from his Lyon, from this bleſſed Sacrament, for our peace and comfort, which now thoſe bitter waters of Meribah, and ſtrife, running downe ſo violently in a floud, doe, in a ſort, waſh off from many a ſeduced and unbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced ſoule! But woe, and alas! how may our mother the Church, well typed in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1079:22"/> Arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> (ſhe is ſo toſſed on the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king billowes of windy, yet boyſterous ſpirits) ſpeake out with <hi>Rebekkah,</hi> when ſhee felt her Twinnes to ſtruggle toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within her, <hi>If it bee ſo,</hi> that I have conceived,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.22.</note> 
               <hi>Why am I thus?</hi> what meanes this ſtrange, and this unnaturall elbow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſhouldring, and juſtling together in the ſame womb betweene Brethren? Its a lamentable thing to behold, how this holy Sacrament, which was ordained by Chriſt to bee a bond, by which wee ſhould bee knit together in unity, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all members of the ſame one Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like body the Church, of which none but Chriſt alone is the myſticall<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22.</note> head; (and therefore it is called by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Communion) ſhould yet from the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate confounding of thoſe things, which in their owne nature are as different as may be, become as 'twere the <hi>Samſon</hi> to teare in pieces the ſtrongeſt<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 16.9.</note> Wyths of union in the Church: and, which is yet the deafneſſe of the aſpe upon the eares of miſſe-lead Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in this divided party, men will not heare
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1079:22"/> the wiſeſt charmings of the beſt charmer, at leaſt, like thoſe at Babel, they will not, though they<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.9.</note> may,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.7.</note> underſtand each other, and all by reaſon of the confuſion of tongues and pens, and thoſe pens dipped often ſo low in vinegar and gall, that as a ſtorme-driven ſhip upon the rockes, the ribs of the common mother the Church be daſhed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in ſunder by the waves of implacable contention.</p>
            <p>Behold, and wonder; here <hi>Manaſſes</hi> is againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> there <hi>Ephraim</hi> is againſt <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> yonder both againſt <hi>Judah:</hi> the Papiſts againſt the Lutherans, the Lutherans againſt them, and both againſt the Calviniſts; as if Chriſt were to bee<note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13.</note> divided, or the truth were more then<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5.</note> one.</p>
            <p>The Lutheran,<note place="margin">The Luth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ran conſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> in as much as Chriſts bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature ſubſiſteth not but in and with the infiniteneſſe of the ſecond Perſon in the Trinity, by vertue of the ineffable union hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaticall, hath given unto the ſame hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature of Chriſt a participated Ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with the Divinity, which is every
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1079:23"/> where, at all times, and as Philoſophers ſay of the ſoule informing the body, its <hi>tota in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, &amp; tota in qualibet parte,</hi> wholly every where, and ſo with the Sacrament; by meanes whereof Chriſt is corporally, by a kinde of Conſubſtantiation (as their word is) [in] or [under] the Sacramentall ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: But this opinion firſt ſeemeth to be injurious to the Divinity, as if it were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded together with it, contrary to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Creed of<note n="k" place="margin">One Chriſt, not by [confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on] of ſubſtance, but by unitie of Perſon.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> and withall, it doth indeed overthrow the truth of his humanity: for firſt, though Chriſts humane nature was for<note n="l" place="margin">See the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Edw. Reynolds</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> meditation on the Lo. laſt Supper.</note> production extraordinary, for the communication of glory from the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head on it admirable; yet the Godhead glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies that his humane Nature only to be the head, that is, to be the moſt excellent, and firſt-borne of every Creature, but not to make it ſhare in the eſſentiall properties of the Divine Nature it ſelfe, ſuch as are Ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity or omnipreſency, immenſity, infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. for if ſo, then the humane Nature were not onely glorified, and exalted, but the very ſame with the Divinity it ſelfe; for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1079:23"/> that Eſſence, or being to which the intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and originally eſſentiall attributes of any thing doe belong, in the ſame degree, that they are in it ſelfe, that thing muſt needs be of the ſame nature with that from which it doth receive thoſe attributes. Now Gods infinite Being every where, wholly, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes at the ſame time (for he is that intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall ſphere whoſe center is every where, and circumference no where) is an eſſentiall property incommunicable from the infinite divine Nature, to the humane Nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the humane Nature is incapable of ſuch an attribute, in ſo infinite a degree; it being all out (in its owne kinde) as eſſentiall to its ſelfe to be finite, to be circumſcribed in a place, &amp;c. as it is to the Godhead to be moſt infinitely every where; and ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that Philoſophicall Maxime, <hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid recipitur, recipitur ad modum recipientis,</hi> there is too infinite a diſproportion betweene the finite humane Nature, and the Divine, that it is not capable of that infinite attribute of Ubiquity: therefore though <hi>Totus Chriſtus,</hi> whole Chriſt be every where, by meanes of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1079:24"/> the union hypoſtaticall, yet not <hi>Totum Chriſti,</hi> the whole of Chriſt, by reaſon of the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedneſſe of his finite humane Nature to one place now in Heaven. In ſhort, Chriſts Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the Union received an extraordinary exaltation, but yet no deſtruction of its own eſſentiall properties, for ſo the Nature it ſelfe were utterly overthrowne: yea more, by this Gods owne omnipotency is impaired; for howbeit God can do all things Poſsible, yet they be ſuch all things, <hi>quae poſſe, perfectae potentiae eſt,</hi> ſay your greateſt<note n="m" place="margin">Vid. Halenſ. par. <hi>1.</hi> quaeſt. <hi>21.</hi> mem. <hi>1.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>101.</hi> edit. <hi>1622.</hi> item P. Lumb. l. <hi>1.</hi> diſt. <hi>42.</hi> E.</note> School-men, and ſuch as imply neither any contradiction to his owne Nature in himſelfe, no nor to the nature of any Creature, as<note n="n" place="margin">Zanch. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de nat. Dei cap. <hi>1.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Zanchy</hi> ſaith, [ſo] as it was created. If therefore it be the eſſentiall property, as it is, of the humane Nature to be finite, and ſo to be confined to heaven as one place, it were a contradiction to Gods all-mightineſſe (according to the ordinary oeconomy and diſpenſation of his providence) to make it, being circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed already, to be infinitely elſewhere at the ſame inſtant. Chriſts preſence in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then being intended of that Nature,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1079:24"/> wherein he was our Redeemer, which was his humane, and not his divine onely; by this that I have ſaid its cleare, that this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation of the Lutherans is unſolid.</p>
            <p>Next comes in the Papiſt,<note place="margin">The Papiſticall Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</note> and with him brings in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> too, his ſleeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe tale of Tranſubſtantiation, (as a<note n="o" place="margin">My L. Biſh. of Exon. ſect. <hi>18.</hi> No peace with Rome.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Prelate calls it;) by others, its named <hi>commentum,</hi> a meere fictitious, and faigned thing, ſo the<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Centur.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4 <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>edit.</hi> 1624.</note> Centuriatours; by others, <hi>ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> ſo he who was no more in name then nature the<note n="q" place="margin">Juel. Apol. p. <hi>40.</hi> vol. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Juel</hi> of his time, in his divine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology: at the beſt, we may all ſtile the tales they have about it, as <hi>Amphilochius</hi> doth thoſe that the Poets tell of their gods,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Amphiloch. in Iambis, ad Selcucum.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Fables, of laughter worthy, and of teares:</l>
               </q> yea, I had almoſt ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And this was likewiſe brought both into the world, and upon the ſtage by that other fable of the multi-preſence of Chriſts body: and it ſounds the better like a tale, becauſe indeed they ſo much vary among themſelves in telling of it: fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands they have in their<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 15.4.</note> tayles to burne
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1079:25"/> downe the ripe corn-fields of Truth, but yet as <hi>Samſons</hi> foxes they are divided in the heads. Once for all,<note n="c" place="margin">Alphonſus à Caſtro, l. <hi>8</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. haer. p. <hi>578</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro</hi> (an ingenuous Romaniſt, in my opinion) down right confeſſeth, that the mention of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation of the bread into the body of Chriſt is rare in ancient Writers; and yet<note n="d" place="margin">See Hooker, l. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>195. 196.</hi>
               </note> Antiquity, when<note n="e" place="margin">Bene [iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data] antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, <hi>Vincent. Lyrin. cap</hi> 6. <hi>adverſ. haereſ. Confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cum ib. cap.</hi> 9.25, 26, 27, 29, 41, 42, 43.</note> True, is an admirable ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tler of Truth: ſo is the word in <hi>Tertullian, Quod primum, verum;</hi> the nigher the Primitive, ſtill the<note n="f" place="margin">The more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient things, the more uncorrupt. Biſhop Bilſon, preface to the perpet. govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, pag. <hi>10.</hi> vol. <hi>4.</hi> and in that booke often theſe two are coupled together, <hi>viz.</hi> The ancient and incorrupt Church and witneſſes.</note> purer, and leſſe corrupt: And who knowes not the old word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and the Prophet<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>Jeremies</hi> exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Stand, and aske for the old way, that's the ſure way to finde reſt to your ſoules: And yet who ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Thraſoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call oſtentatours of antiquity as theſe? But ſurely this their pleading for the<note n="h" place="margin">My Lord Biſhop Morton, now of Dureſme, Epiſt. Dedicat. to King <hi>Charles</hi> before the Grand Impoſt.</note> New-old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (as a worthy Prelate calls it) of it, is, as were the Gibeonites pretences of [<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh</hi> 9.</note> torne] ſhooes, and [mouldy] bread, by which they fained themſelves to have come from [far.] This dreame of Tranſubſtantiation was
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1079:25"/> broached, or hammered out at firſt by one, who was, ſome ſay, a Magitian, and 'twas withſtood by<note n="k" place="margin">Iren. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and<note n="l" place="margin">Epiphan. haer. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter urged againe by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth, but withſtood by <hi>Berengarius</hi> a Deacon, for which he was condemned as an Hereticke <hi>in Concilio Vercellenſi:</hi> and this was betweene the yeares 1049. and 1055. if<note n="m" place="margin">Platin. in vita Leon. noni.</note> 
               <hi>Platina,</hi> in the life of <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth, faile not in his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology: Here he was condemned; after, ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>Nicholas</hi> the ſecond, and one <hi>Albericus</hi> a Deacon, to a groſſe and ſhamefull recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as the ſame<note n="n" place="margin">Idem in vita Nicolai ſecund.</note> authour reporteth, out of <hi>Lanfrancus.</hi> Betweene this time, and the Councell of Lateran, which was under <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius</hi> the third (<hi>Anno</hi> 1215.) that great learned Phyſician and Philoſopher <hi>Averroes</hi> lived, and tooke ſcandall at the whole body of Chriſtian religion for this, as<note n="o" place="margin">Eſpencaeus, l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. adorat.</note> 
               <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> ſaith: in the yeere 1215. it was decreed firſt, in the firſt Canon of the Councell of<note n="p" place="margin">Carranza, p. <hi>420</hi> ſum. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. vol. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Lateran; at what time the Greeke Church had ſevered themſelves from them, and was withſtood by <hi>Bertram,</hi> the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">See my Lord Biſh. Morton, cap. <hi>15.</hi> ſect. <hi>19.</hi> theſ. <hi>6.</hi> pag. <hi>398.</hi> edit. <hi>2.</hi> Grand Impoſtare.</note> 
               <hi>Albigenſes</hi> in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1079:26"/> till at laſt it was foyſted in among the twenty new Articles, or above, of the Creed of the conventicle at<note n="a" place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Trident. ſeſſ. <hi>13.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Trent, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with an Anathema, as of abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to ſalvation to be beleeved by the people. But yet this Doctrine was ſhortly after by<note n="b" place="margin">Chemnit. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. part. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>136, 137,</hi> &amp;c. vol. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chemnitius,</hi> and ſince by many other of our own Worthies, diſcovered to be a piece of<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Goſpel from S. <hi>Pauls;</hi> and therefore as the ſerpent of<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>Aaron</hi> devoured the ſerpents of the Magitians of Egypt, even ſo that one<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9.</note> Anathema of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> muſt needs condemn all the Anathema's, which they from that<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.13.</note> Ebal of theirs denounce in the defence of that, which is not the faith [<note n="g" place="margin">Jud. ver. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] once delivered to the Saints, and but once for all, in the dayes of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Now they ſnarle much among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the beſt bone of their expreſsions herein. The Maſter of the Sentences confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in ſo great variety his<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>P. Lumbard, l.</hi> 4. <hi>diſt:</hi> 11. <hi>A.</hi> Si quaeritur, qualis ſit illa converſio, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite non ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio.</note> inſufficiency to define the right:<note n="i" place="margin">Bellarm. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi> de Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine;</hi> their great Champion, will not have by the pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of theſe foure words [This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.] any productive, or conſervative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1079:26"/> of the bread into the body of Chriſt, but by a new langled device, an adductive; His reaſon is, becauſe the body of Chriſt [was] before this converſion, but not under the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of bread; which is meere Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>location, nor Tranſubſtantiation for if ſo,<note place="margin">What Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation is.</note> there muſt be a change of one ſubſtance into another, and that Chriſts reall and true bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is made of the bread, and the bread chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into it, which is properly Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, as our moſt reverend<note n="l" place="margin">My L. Grace againſt A.C. ſect. <hi>38.</hi> num. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>327, 328.</hi>
               </note> Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane hath ſhewen us: and if it be a Tranſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, then not <hi>abique,</hi> and if as a ſubſtance under the accidents of the colour of bread and wine, then being a [bodily] ſubſtance, it muſt be <hi>in loco,</hi> and circumſcribed, either way its contradiction.</p>
            <p>Another of their graver Divines, is<note n="m" place="margin">Cornelius à Lapide, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Iſa. <hi>7.14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius a Lapide,</hi> the Jeſuite, who faith, that by the words of conſecration, Truely and real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the bread is tranſubſtantiated, ſo Chriſt is produced, and as it were generated upon the Altar in ſuch a powerfull and effectuall manner, <hi>ut ſi Chriſtus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecdion eſſet incarnatus, per haec verba [Hoc eſt corpus meum] incarnare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1079:27"/> corpuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> humanum aſſumeret,</hi> That if Chriſt had not yet beene incarnate, by theſe foure words [This is my body] he ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate, and take an humane body. What is to be mad, if this be to be ſober? yea, how doth this grate upon the foundation of the faith of the incarnation?</p>
            <p>And ſurely much of this proceedeth from their not allowing any Tropes, or Figures, (which yet is contrary to the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of whom notwithſtanding they bragge ſo much) in Sacramentall ſpeeches, though the Scripture abounds this way: ſo Circumciſion is called the Covenant, becauſe it was the<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10, 11.</note> token of the Covenant, and the<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</note> Seal of the ſame; and in this very buſineſſe of the Supper its moſt apparent, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in that one place of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16. [The cup of bleſsing which we bleſſe,<note place="margin">Sacramentall ſpeeches are tropicall.</note> is it not the communion of the bloud of Chriſt? The bread which wee breake, is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt?] In this paſſage, [The cup of bleſsing which wee bleſſe] there are three Tropes: 1. Firſt, the cup, metonymically put for the wine in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1079:27"/> cup. 2. The wine, by a metonymie of the ſubject, is put for the drinking of the wine. 3. Its called the cup of bleſsing, by a meto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymie of the adjunct, becauſe it hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing adjoyned to it; and that bleſsing is put for thankſgiving, Prayer, declaration of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: as if he had ſaid, The drinking of the wine conſecrated, which we bleſſe, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie, and over which we give thanks, Is it not the communion of the bloud of Chriſt? This interrogation affirmeth with more ſtrength, Yes, it is the communion, that is, ſay ſome, the ſigne; ſay others, the ſeale and obſignation; ſay a third ſort, the declaration; and ſome, the inſtrumentall meanes of the communion which the true Beleever hath with Chriſt in his bloud: ſo that the ſenſe amounts to this, The drinking of the wine conſecrated, is a ſigne of our communion with Chriſt; all which is couched under theſe Tropicall expreſsions. Beſides, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, even [after] conſecration calleth it the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.29.</note> fruit of the vine; and Saint<note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> [after] too,<note n="q" place="margin">See my Lord Biſh. of Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> c. <hi>15.</hi> ſect. <hi>24.</hi> theſ. <hi>2</hi> p. <hi>403, 404.</hi> Grand Impoſt.</note> bread and cup. Moreover, if we mark it well, the ſubject of that Sacramentall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1079:28"/> that is, the demonſtrative par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle [This] can have reference to no other ſubſtance, but that which our Saviour held in his ſacred hands, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pronomen [hoc] demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtravit panem materialem.</hi> Franciſcus Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon noſter, l. <hi>5.</hi> de miniſter. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glic. cap. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>604.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>panem materialem,</hi> to the materiall bread and wine, which are of ſo different a nature from the body, and bloud of Chriſt, that the one cannot poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, in proper ſenſe, or but common reaſon, be ſaid to be the other: and againe, in the predicate, or the latter part of the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, there is not mention made onely of Chriſts body and bloud, but of his body
[broken,] and his bloud [ſhed,] to ſhew, that his body is to be conſidered here<note n="b" place="margin">My Lo. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh, cap. <hi>4.</hi> of the Iriſh Relig.</note> apart, not as it was borne of the Virgin, or now is in Heaven, but as it was [broken] and [cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified] for us; and his bloud likewiſe apart, not as running in his veines, but as [ſhed] out of his body; which the Rhemiſts have told us to be conditions of his perſon, as he was in ſacrifice, and oblation. Beſides, they are bid to doe this, in [remembrance] of him: Now [<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25.</note> remembrance] is of things
[abſent] at leaſt; and if in remembrance, then (which I note by the way) we may ſee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1079:28"/> whether the Romane Church did ever erre, or not, when for 600. yeares together it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed (though ſince indeed it be rejected) the ſentence of <hi>Innocentius</hi> the firſt, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned the Euchariſt to be adminiſtred even unto<note n="d" place="margin">Maldonat. Jeſuit. in Joh. <hi>6.53.</hi> &amp; Eſpencae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de adorat. eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> Idem probat Binius ex re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. Innoc. Pap. tom <hi>1.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. p. <hi>585.</hi> edit. <hi>1606.</hi>
               </note> Infants, who through want of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot poſsibly [Remember] what they are not yet capable to Know. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point, to ſhew that all this is to be meant onely in a [<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.63.</note> ſpirituall] way, and that this is a<note n="f" place="margin">Convivium tam
[ſublime] &amp; tam [ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuale.] Rabbi Samuel Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lita, ociundus de civitate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Morochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani, ad Rabbi Iſaac, Magiſtr. Synagogae, <hi>cap.</hi> 20. <hi>p.</hi> 646. <hi>in Parr.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſublime, and myſticall banquet, as even a Jewiſh Rabbi 600. yeares agoe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, it is to be noted, that Chriſt ſaith firſt, [Take, eat,] and then, This is my body, to intimate unto us, as learned,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hooker lib.</hi> 5. 359.</note> 
               <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> obſerveth, that the Sacrament, however changed by conſecration from common uſe, yet is never properly to be called the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, till [taken, and eaten,] by means of which actions, (if they bee actions of faith) that holy bread and wine doe as real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as meanes and inſtruments) convey whole Chriſt, with the vitall influences that proceed from him into the ſoule, as the hand doth them unto the mouth, or the mouth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1079:29"/> unto the ſtomacke. Wherefore is then this ſo great adoe? Surely<note n="h" place="margin">Chemnit. quâ ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Chemnitius</hi> ſheweth plainly to be, becauſe the Sacrifice of the Maſſe may be ſupported, aſſervation, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumgeſtation may be upheld, that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh<note n="*" place="margin">My Lo. of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſm, quae ſupra p. <hi>403, 404.</hi>
               </note> Moloch, Chriſts ſubſtance corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under the colour, and <hi>ſpecies</hi> of bread and wine may be adored, and that Chriſt by this dreame, being corporally preſent, might, though onely as a ſacrifice unbloudy, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually offered up upon their ſuperſtitious, I had almoſt ſaid Idoll-Altars: when yet, the Scripture tells us plainly, that as men dye but once for all, no more is Chriſt offered up, (ſave onely Euchariſtically, and<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chryſ. hom. <hi>17</hi> in Heb.</note> comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moratively, and by way of<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>[Reprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatio] ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii.</hi> P. Lumb. l. <hi>4,</hi> diſt. <hi>12</hi> G. confer Du Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin, Art. <hi>9.</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus fin. defence of K. <hi>James.</hi>
               </note> Repreſentation) but once for all, hylaſtically and in propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the iteration, and repeating of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice implying imperfection, and inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency under the old law, Chriſts owne ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of himſelfe upon the Croſſe, moſt complete perfection, becauſe but once for all, Heb. 9.27, 28.</p>
            <p>And as they are thus groſſely out in this proviſion it ſelfe, <hi>viz.</hi> the fleſh and bloud of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1079:29"/> Chriſt; ſo doe they become injurious alſo to it in the uſage of it, They by oblation, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, circumgeſtation, and carrying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, adoration, and the like, prophane it; Whereas the actions enjoyned to us herein, are Sacramentall only, expreſſed in the Text, by [eating and by drinking;] which is the next particular, though but in a little mouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of words onely, to bee diſcourſed of: <hi>Whoſo</hi> [eateth] <hi>my fleſh, and</hi> [drinketh] <hi>my bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe actions of [Eating,<note place="margin">The third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</note> and of Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king] are both of Sacramentall Inſtitution, and ſignification, ſymbolically repreſenting the inward application of, and as it were the myſticall maſtication, or feeding upon Chriſts fleſh and bloud by faith, which is the mouth of the ſoule, and her exerciſe, and acts about this myſtery, as 'twere, the very eating and the drinking of Chriſts fleſh, and bloud. Now this eating is, as Chriſts body, to which it doth relate, twofold. 1. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall. 2. Spirituall: both are required, but chiefly the ſpirituall, becauſe the wicked may equally ſhare with us in the firſt; and if we have the ſecond, though neceſsity per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1079:30"/> barre us of the firſt, yet we are ſafe: (ſtill remembring the Rule, that <hi>Nuda carentia non damnat,</hi> but <hi>contemptus;</hi> becauſe that Chriſt doth not univerſally, and alwayes<note n="l" place="margin">Deus grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis non alliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, quaſi abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illis neque poſsit, neque velit ullos ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare. <hi>Pet. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. loc. com. claſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>ſect.</hi> 16. <hi>p.</hi> 826.</note> tye, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any exception, his ſaving graces to the outward means:) Hence is that of<note n="m" place="margin">P. Lumb. l. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lumbard,</hi> Some, ſaith he, take both the Sacrament, and the thing ſignified with it, ſo the Elect and faithfull, in their health, or well-diſpoſed; ſome the Sacrament onely, and no more, ſo the Hypocrite; a third ſort, the thing onely, without the ſigne, which is indeed the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall eating: hence is that knowne word of S.<note n="n" place="margin">Aug. Tract. <hi>25.</hi> in Joh.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin, Ut quid paras ventrem, &amp; dentem? crede &amp; manducaſti:</hi> Why prepareſt thou thy teeth, and belly? beleeve only, and thou haſt eaten Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now though I might here take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion juſtly to exhort my ſelfe, and you, to a frequent partaking of Chriſt, even Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally too; and ſo<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.16.</note> redeem the time of our freedome herein, becauſe the dayes are evill, ſo that we may either be taken from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, or it from us: we finde that the Primitive Church was
[<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.46.</note> daily] in it; which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1079:30"/> made Saint<note n="q" place="margin">S. Cyprian. in orat. Dom. ſect. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> to interpret the [daily Bread,] in the Lords prayer, of the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bread: And in Saint <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> dayes there was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
[<note n="a" place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>3.</hi> ad Epheſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] a [daily] ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice in uſe, and he in wonder cryed out on the ſlacke comming unto the holy Altar, and blamed it as an ill cuſtome: But though I urge not ſuch a frequency, leſt the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe might abate ſomewhat of the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to it; yet at leaſt, let not the moone pace over the Zodiack oftner (ſith the ſpouſe of Chriſt is likened to the<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.10.</note> moone) then we performe, if poſsible, our courſe this way. St. <hi>Paul</hi> is at his [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] his [<note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26</note> oftenneſſe,] of which<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 3 <hi>qu.</hi> 66 <hi>art.</hi> 9. <hi>ad</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">um</hi> 
                  <hi>in fine.</hi> Quia homo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel naſcitur, multoties au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem cibatur; ſemel tantum datur baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, multoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens autem Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtia.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas</hi> gives a reaſon (though Baptiſme be but once for all adminiſtred) becauſe though man be but once borne, yet becauſe he ſtands in need of often feeding, and nouriſhment; therefore though the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Initiation, Baptiſme, be but once given, yet the Sacrament of farther confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and ſtrengthening, the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or the Euchariſt, is often adminiſtred. <hi>In Concilio Agathenſi,</hi> as I find in <hi>Iſidores</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, he was ſentenced for an unſound Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1079:31"/> who did not at the three great Feſtivals of the yeere at leaſt communicate: Our own Church hath preſſed her children to<note n="e" place="margin">Canon. Angl. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> Three times a yeare at the leaſt, whereof one to be now at<note n="f" place="margin">Certum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus quia Chriſtus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurgens ex mortuis, jam non moritur, &amp;c. tamen ne obliviſcamur, quod ſemel factum eſt, in memoria no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra omni anno fit, ſc. quotiens [Paſcha] cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratur. <hi>Auguſt. praef. in</hi> 2. <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. Pſal.</hi> 21. <hi>de conſ. diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>apud Lumb. l</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 12. <hi>G.</hi>
               </note> Eaſter: But as for our [ſpirituall] eating, that muſt be every day, for elſe the ſoule would ſtarve and dye, which liveth not but by the<note n="g" place="margin">Hab. <hi>2.4. &amp;</hi> Gal. <hi>3.11.</hi> The fourth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</note> life of faith.</p>
            <p>And as Chriſts fleſh muſt thus be [eaten] by us, ſo muſt every good Chriſtian
[drink] his bloud too; for w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> cauſe we find a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction coupling them both together in the Text: And both bread and wine too were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured in <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> his oblation of both bread and wine to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 14.18. as St.<note n="h" place="margin">S. Cyprian. ſect. <hi>2.</hi> de Coen. Dom.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rabbi Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, quâ ſupra cap. <hi>19.</hi> p. <hi>645.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rabbi Samuel,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 3. <hi>qu.</hi> 61. <hi>Act.</hi> 3. <hi>ad</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">um</hi>.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Hales, par <hi>4.</hi> qu. <hi>10.</hi> mem. <hi>1.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>223.</hi> edit. <hi>1622.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hales,</hi> and many others have well obſerved. See yet if herein our Romaniſts be not directly Antichriſtian, and both wayes run them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the rockes; the dangerous Scyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.18, 19.</note> adding, on the one ſide, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulphing Charybdis of taking away, on the other ſide; both pernicious. In the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Florence (for loe! a deepe ſilence of this, till that time, in all Antiquity) which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1079:31"/> was but in the yeere 1200. ſome 30. yeares after that <hi>Hugo de S. Victore,</hi> and <hi>P. Lumbard</hi> had vented their conceits herein, (and they were the firſt that made any noiſe about it) (as<note n="m" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Whitaker l. <hi>8.</hi> ſect. <hi>59.</hi> de paradox. cont. Duraeum.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Whitaker,</hi> ſometimes Oracle of the chaire in Cambridge, hath ſhewed us) Then and There they decree for ſeven Sacraments, whereas our Saviour appoints but two: They might as well have ſettled 70. times 7. in the larger acception of the word Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it ſignifies the ſigne of an holy thing in generall. And now here, they man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle the uſe of theſe that our Saviour appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, allowing the cup only unto the Clergy, pretending that Chriſt meant that onely to the Apoſtles, then preſent with him at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; but as well they may ſay the ſame likewiſe for the bread. But beſides the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe inſtitution of our Saviour himſelfe, under both kindes, and not of the bread onely in the maine, the wine being by<note n="n" place="margin">Pet. Martyr. loc. com. claſ. <hi>4.</hi> c <hi>10</hi> ſect. <hi>18.</hi> p. <hi>849.</hi>
               </note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitancy alone conſecrated, as ſome of them doe tell us; not onely the Primitive, but even the whole<note n="o" place="margin">Caſſander conſult. Art. <hi>22.</hi> initio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Catholicke Church of Chriſt, yea, even the purer Romane too, for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1079:32"/> a thouſand yeares continuance (which, had there bin no [expreſſe] appointment, was notwithſtanding of a very<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>The appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved practice of the Saints of God, is equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to a precept. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Sclater, <hi>my father, ſ rm. on</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14. <hi>p</hi> 34. <hi>ſtiled The Miniſters portion, edit. Oxon</hi> 1612. —Illa quae ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantur, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum procul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubio valent; ubique, id eſt, toto terrarum orbe ſemper obſervata, &amp;c. <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Whitak. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cont. Duraeum ſect.</hi> 16.</note> binding obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation) did obſerve it ſo, as <hi>Caſſander,</hi> (one of the chiefeſt Divines of his time) confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: Nor indeed can they themſelves ſhew us<note n="q" place="margin">Quando primùm vige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re coepit in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquibus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiis minimè conſtat. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. Jeſ. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. c.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 499. <hi>ſect.</hi> Haec igitur.</note> when certainly the Communion onely under [one] kinde firſt began; yea, till with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe laſt 400. yeares, which is a very new-antiquity, it had no ſpreading enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment: for <hi>Aquinas</hi> confeſſeth that [un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both kindes] was in uſe even to his times, and he was both<note n="a" place="margin">My L. Grace againſt A.C. ſect. <hi>33.</hi> p. <hi>275, 276.</hi> num. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> borne, and dead, during the reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the third of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; and the [one kinde] was decreed but in the thirteenth Seſsion of the Councell of Conſtance, which is very<note n="b" place="margin">Id. ib. ſect. <hi>38</hi> p. <hi>340.</hi>
               </note> moderne, at leaſt farre downewards from the Primitive and pureſt Church; ſo that I have no other hopes to keepe up your attention, with any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe herein, then to tell you onely as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> was wont to ſay to his Athenian auditors, when they grew remiſſe under his Orations, Here is newes for you; which word
[Newes] though it may ſpur
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1079:32"/> your attention in the liſtening to it, yet it ſhould withall encreaſe your abhorrence of that religion, which is thus patched together with the fragments of<note n="c" place="margin">I will ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely promiſe, that when ever any point of the Religion I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe ſhall be proved to be [new,] and not ancient, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike, I meane for matter of faith, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it, &amp;c. See K. <hi>James</hi> confeſſ. of faith, Art. <hi>23</hi> in fine, exactly.</note> Novelty: for there is no faith, or religion True, but onely That which is Catholike Truely, and properly, which is, and was beleeved every where, alwayes, and by all; which hath, as <hi>Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Vincent. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin. cap. <hi>3.</hi> cont. haereſ. — Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer my Lo. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh, ſer. on Eph. <hi>4.13.</hi> p. <hi>27, 28, 29.</hi> edit. <hi>1631.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lirinenſis</hi> ſaith, both Univerſality, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and unanime Conſent of the<note n="e" place="margin">See Aug. epiſt. <hi>18.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>4.</hi> de Bapt. cont. Donatiſt. c. <hi>24.</hi> —Confer my L. Grace, againſt A.C. ſect. <hi>21.</hi> p. <hi>137, 138.</hi> num. <hi>4.</hi>—&amp; ſect. <hi>38.</hi> p. <hi>352.</hi> num. <hi>17.</hi> initio.—&amp; ſect. <hi>39.</hi> p. <hi>378.</hi> num. <hi>4.</hi> ib.</note> whole Church of Chriſt, which theſe late upſtart devices and<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9.</note> doctrines of men, undoing, by conſequence, the ancient and pure worſhip of God, have not.</p>
            <p>Sith then, my deare Brethren, theſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, the onely [Catholikes] as they cry themſelves up, (by which one<note n="g" place="margin">My L. of Durh. quâ ſupra c. <hi>15.</hi> ſect. <hi>1.</hi> initio.</note> word, as by a <hi>Gorgon</hi>'s, or a <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s head, painted in a ſhield, they thinke at firſt ſight to terrifie and delude poore ignorant Proteſtants, as they count moſt of them, and if they could) ſith I ſay, theſe be ſuch<note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>Hanuns,</hi> to ſhame us by cutting off at [halfes] the beſt of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ornaments, as he did of <hi>Davids</hi> ſervants
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1079:33"/> in a mock; and fith they dare to be ſo bold, as to take from you the<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. <hi>116.13. Calix ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, ſanguis eſt Salvatoris.</hi> Bern. tract. de lib. arbit. &amp; gratia, fol. <hi>289 G.</hi> &amp; Illyr p. <hi>126.</hi> in verbo <hi>Calix.</hi>
               </note> cup of ſalvation, pray you for their converſion, if God<note n="k" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25.</note> peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wil give them repentance to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the truth, and then leave them and their<note n="l" place="margin">This with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt is all the infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity the Pope hath, to be ſure to be infallible in whatſoever he
[would] have determined: chiefly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and Baſil. See my L. Grace; qua ſupra, ſect. <hi>29.</hi> num. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>219</hi> &amp; ſect. <hi>33</hi> ib. p. <hi>262, 263,</hi> &amp;c.</note> infallible Head (if ſo they will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne) unto Gods cup of Trembling, which ſhall make them reel, and ſtagger more with Terrour, then exceſſe: And for your ſelves, liſten to your dearly-loving Saviours in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation, who ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>Come</hi> unto me: <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come unto me, and drinke,</hi> Joh. 7.37. What is this thirſt, but a thirſt of faith? for ſo verſe 38. and what is this drinke, but the precious liquour of his owne bloud? for as hee ſaith, Joh. 6.55. in the next verſe to my Text, My fleſh is [meat] indeed, ſo alſo, My bloud is [drinke] indeed; whereof this Sacramentall cup, (tendred unto every of you by us, deare Chriſtians, that be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers by faith of Chriſt, according to his owne appointment and inſtitution) is the ſure ſigne, and ſeale, and pledge unto your ſoules. For this cauſe, yee ſee clearely, in the Text, that by a copulative, both Eating and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1079:33"/> Drinking are conjoyned together: what therefore God hath thus joyned together, let no man (much leſſe the<note n="l" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.</note> man of ſinne, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be conſumed by the<note n="m" place="margin">Verſ. <hi>8.</hi> ib.</note> ſpirit of Chriſts mouth) dare to put<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.6.</note> aſunder: and ſith both are ſo placed in the Text, that as the<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.20</note> Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims on the mercy ſeat, though they look each to other, yet ſtill turning with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the mercy ſeat, ſo both theſe to the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall particle, that is ſet in the doore of my Text, to call in all worthy commers; Loe! every one, all ye that hunger and thirſt aright by faith, come in, and eat, and drinke your fill, ſaith Chriſt; Behold, my owne fleſh and bloud ſtand ready fitted for your beſt proviſion: and to ſet an edge upon your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall appetites, ſee, here is after Supper, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life to abide with you, and you with it for ever, and this moſt fully to bee given at the laſt act; for ſo we read, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Whoſo, Whoſoever eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud</hi> [hath eternall life.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hath eternall life.]</hi> See here, and note it,<note place="margin">The third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</note> No man ever yet loſt by his obedience to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1079:34"/> Chriſt; he is not<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10.</note> unrighteous to forget it: hee alone is worthy to loſe, who when Chriſt inviteth him, he puts him off with fond<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.18.</note> excuſes, and will not come: loe! here is [life] given, the ſweeteſt monoſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the world, and not ſo alone, but life [eternall:] Had he ſaid length of daies, he had made good the firſt promiſe made to the obedience of the morall law, Eph. 6.3. but in that he names eternall life, ſee here the complement of all bliſſe. But I pray note the expreſsion, 'tis in the preſent tenſe,
[<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] not he [ſhall] have, but he [hath] it: and how ſo? becauſe a beleever thus feeding upon Chriſt by faith, hath Chriſt himſelfe, who is ſtiled eternall life, Joh. 17.3. for Chriſt by faith<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17.</note> dwelleth in ſuch an one, and he in him, Joh. 6.56. yea Chriſt himſelfe ſaith as much, Joh. 11.25. I am the life, and hee that beleeveth in me ſhall never dye, for he hath in him life eternall.</p>
            <p>Again, if eternall life be here ſet, as I think it is, as the Reward of faith, then how hath the beleever it already? <hi>Anſ. In Spe,</hi> though not <hi>in Re;</hi> In hope and expectation he hath
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1079:34"/> it, though not in actually complete fruition; and by this hope they are<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24.</note> ſaved: Or elſe they have it, <hi>in arrhabone,</hi> in the<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14.</note> earneſt, <hi>&amp; in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillo,</hi> in the<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30.</note> ſeale, and marke of the ſpirit, which marke is for ever indeleble; it's as a foundation,<note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19</note> ſure, not to be ſhaken, no not by all the machinations, or<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18.</note> policies of Hell it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But how ſo, ſith they that beleeve dye? <hi>Anſ.</hi> What of that? ſith he that beleeveth in Chriſt, though he were<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.25.</note> dead, yet ſhall hee live: Dye hee muſt, becauſe of the ſtatute, Heb. 9.27. But let not this trouble the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; for as Chriſt is the life, ſo is he alſo the reſurrection too: and therefore, in the Text, it's added, by way of aſſurance, that I will raiſe him up at the laſt day: and I like<note n="*" place="margin">Beza ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> his gueſſe well, that [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] here ſtands for [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] that the [and] here is a cauſall note, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by way of <hi>prolepſis,</hi> or of preoccupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to remove that objection, likely to bee raiſed by a weakling, though a Beleever, Thus: You promiſe life eternall, and loe! I die, where then is your promiſe? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Why? I will raiſe thee up againe, at the laſt day:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1079:35"/> and if yee note it, at your leiſure, you ſhall finde this ſpeech of the Reſurrection no leſſe then<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 6, 39, 40, 44, 54.</note> foure times, in this one Chapter, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, to double the obſervation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall part.</note>And at this ſaying of a Reſurrection at the laſt day, we may well reſume that of the Diſciples, <hi>John.</hi> 6.60. <hi>Durus eſt hic ſermo,</hi> This is a hard ſaying, who can beare it? Surely no unbeleeving, meerely naturall man on earth: yea, more then ſo, the very Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles themſelves were<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.25.</note> ſlow of heart at the firſt to beleeve it; and the reports of thoſe good ſoules, the women that having ſeene Chriſt after his Reſurrection, told it to the Diſciples, ſeemed to them as<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.11.</note> idle tales, ſaith S. <hi>Luke,</hi> cap. 24.11. yea, S. <hi>Thomas</hi> expreſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, that for his part hee would<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 20.25.</note> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it, till he felt him, <hi>John</hi> 20.25. The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers at Athens derided the doctrine, and made a mock of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when hee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it to them, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.32. At other times, he was not onely called in<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 23.6.</note> queſtion, but in danger almoſt to be torne in<note n="u" place="margin">Ver. <hi>10.</hi> ib.</note> pieces for the ſame: the<note n="x" place="margin">Ver. <hi>8.</hi> ib.</note> Sadducees, a certaine ſect in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1079:35"/> dayes, yea riſe alſo in our<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 22.23.</note> Saviours owne time, flatly denied that there was any Reſurrection, or Angel, or Spirit; for alas! the poring eye of<note n="z" place="margin">To conceive of Divine things by Philoſophy, is no other then to take out a red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hot Iron with our fingers, and not with tongs. My L. of Exon, Sect. <hi>18.</hi> No peace with Rome</note> Nature was too dimme to diſcerne ſo high a myſtery as this was, ſo farre remote from her beſt-diſpoſed Organs: The wiſeſt Ethnick was no better at this then S. <hi>Peters</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one that was pur-blind, like to a Bat or Owle, or like S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> man betweene ſleeping and waking. That Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principle of, <hi>à privatione ad habitum non datur regreſſus,</hi> that from a totall privation of life from the Body, there was no poſsibility of a returne, was ſo faſtened in them, that like to a firſt Principle, or a Mathematicall Rule, it muſt be taken True for granted, and he that ſhould offer a diſputation againſt it, he was, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> at Athens, to be eſteemed a<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.18.</note> Babler, or as a Naturall <hi>Ignaro;</hi> the ground of all is, becauſe this is a buſineſſe meerely of Faith, to which all Carnall<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 8. <hi>ad</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">um</hi> Oportet quòd naturalis ratio ſubſerviat fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei.</note> Reaſonings muſt give way: in the Naturall man, both the <hi>medium,</hi> which is Faith, is wanting, or unprepared, and the object, Chriſt riſen, ſtood at too great a diſtance to bee kenned,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1079:36"/> no not ſo much as <hi>Moſes</hi> did from mount<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.1.</note> Nebo the land of promiſe [a farre off] by him; It's the proper work of Gods ſpirit only, as he did thoſe Dead bones in<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.14.</note> 
               <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> (which were a figure of the Reſurrection) to quicken and enliven his firſt apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and faith for this purpoſe. Some Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques there were, after the Apoſtles dayes, in<note n="f" place="margin">Tertul. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. adv. Haer. c. <hi>46, 48, 49, 51</hi> Saturn. Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Carpocrates, Cerdon, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullians</hi> time, that were againſt the Bodily Reſurrection: the Anabaptiſts, and Libertines of late, were all for the Spirituall Reſurrection of the ſoule from ſinne unto the life of grace in this life; though that good Martyr <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> S. <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciple, ſtileth ſuch, whether Epicures, or others,<note n="g" place="margin">Polycarpus Epiſt. ad Philip.</note> 
               <hi>Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitos Satanae,</hi> the firſt-begotten of Satan; yea, even<note n="h" place="margin">Tertul. lib. de Monogam.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> himſelfe, that ancient Father of the Church, after his infection by the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of <hi>Montanus,</hi> whom hee ſtiled his Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clete, and his Prophet;<note n="i" place="margin">Lactant. lib. <hi>7.</hi> inſtit. Div. c. <hi>21, 24, 26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> alſo, and divers other Doctors of the Church, having a tang of the errour of the Millenaries, theſe, though they granted a Reſurrection to bee, yet were out in the underſtanding of it: for, miſ-underſtanding that Prophecy <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1079:36"/> where there is mention of a [firſt] Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, imagined that there ſhould be a [firſt] Reſurrection of the Juſt, that ſhould raigne here a thouſand yeares even upon [earth;] and after that, a ſecond Reſurrection of the Wicked, at the day of the generall judgment: Whereas we know, there ſhall bee but<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 11.24.</note> one [generall] Reſurrection of the Bodies of the juſt, and unjuſt at the laſt day; that firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection in S. <hi>John</hi> being to be underſtood onely of the inward, and ſpirituall Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſoule out of the grave of ſinne, which, as a body in the grave, lies too much rotting, and corrupting of the ſoule; for which cauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath called it the<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. <hi>ſee Rom.</hi> 6.</note> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſts Reſurrection. Theſe ſome then, and divers more that might happely be named, have either flatly denied, or elſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneouſly miſtaken this doctrine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: the more are we all, my beloved, from this meditation bound to thanke our good God, who hath ſo bleſſed us, with<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3.</note> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bleſsings in Chriſt Jeſus, that he hath given us better eyes, by means of the vaile of naturall blindneſſe removed, to ſee into this
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1079:37"/> great myſtery of godlineſſe, and hath let this part of the<note n="n" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</note> light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, in the knowledge of his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſhine into our hearts.</p>
            <p>My purpoſe was not, on this occaſion, to dwell at large upon this Common place of the Reſurrection now: onely Two things I note, as Principally here intended. Firſt, the Author of the Beleevers Reſurrection, Chriſt himſelfe, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I, Emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally I, will raiſe him up, What ſtronger ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Divine Nature of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? Noe [man] (meerely) ſuch, hath ever quickened his<note n="o" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5, 6.</note> owne ſoule, but Chriſt doth this <hi>Poteſtative,</hi> by vertue of his own innate Power, for ſo he ſaith, I have<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 10.18.</note> power to lay downe my life, and I have power to take it up againe; and therefore ſaith<note n="q" place="margin">Bern. ſer. <hi>10.</hi> de Paſch.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard,</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferencing Chriſts from all others Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Reliqui ſuſcitantur, ſolus Chriſtus Reſurrexit:</hi> Well may others be [raiſed,] Chriſt onely [roſe,] hee onely by
[himſelfe] could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer death: Wherefore, though the originall word, in <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.6.
[<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] be paſsive, yet muſt it bee underſtood actively, as a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1079:37"/> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Bp. Lake, on <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>15.20.</hi> p. <hi>157.</hi>
               </note> Prelate hath obſerved: This power manifeſted in Chriſts Reſurrection was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, ſay<note n="ſ" place="margin">Albinus quaeſt. in Gen.</note> 
               <hi>Albinus,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Julianus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merius, lib. <hi>1.</hi> contr. Judaeos p. <hi>556.</hi> in Patr. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Julianus Pomerius,</hi> and others greatly learned, in that prophecy of old <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 49.9. where <hi>Juda</hi> is ſaid to ſtoupe down, and to couch as an old Lyon, and yet, ſaith the ſame great Patriarch, as a Lyons whelp from the prey, my ſonne, thou art gone up: this is a cleare Type of our Lord and Saviour, who by S. <hi>John</hi> is called the<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 5.5.</note> Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> who, during the Time of his paſsion, and his humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeemed to couch as it were, and to lie downe in his grave, as an old and weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lyon; but as a Lyon that is young, in much ſtrength, hee rouzeth up himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, having broken the bonds of<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.24, 31.</note> Death, and Hell in his victorious Reſurrection: ſo that this [taking up] of his life againe ſheweth the Truth of his Divinity, and om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent conſubſtantiality,<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6.</note> equall with his eternall Father, and the holy Ghoſt; that hee was not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, onely [like] unto, but verily <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the [ſame] ſubſtance with his Father, againſt that damnable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1079:38"/> of <hi>Arrius,</hi> under which though the<note n="n" place="margin">Haereſis Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii prorupit, totum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> [or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem] invecto errore turba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verat. <hi>Sulpic. Severus l.</hi> 2. <hi>ſacr. hiſt. p.</hi> 144. <hi>in</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>cum Druſio.</hi>
               </note> world ſeemed in the dayes of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> the Great, in a ſort, to<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>[Ingemuit] totus orbis, &amp; Arrianum ſe eſſe miratus eſt.</hi> Hieron. cont. Luciferian.— Confer Hooker, l. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>266.</hi> ad p. <hi>274.</hi> Et D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Field, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> in medio. My L. of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſme, c. <hi>15</hi> ſect. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>368.</hi> qua ſupra. Et M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wotton, ſerm. <hi>2.</hi> in Joh. p. <hi>77, 78,</hi> &amp;c.</note> groane, yet was it condemned in the firſt generall Councell at Nice, and himſelfe at laſt voyded with his<note n="p" place="margin">Ruffin. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> hiſt. Eccleſ.</note> bowels, and entrals, as he was about to go to maintaine his blaſphemy, his ſoule out of his body, being ſmitten by the immediate hand of Divine Juſtice for his obſtinacie herein.</p>
            <p>Now as this ſheweth the Divinitie, ſo in that in the former part of the Text, he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth his fleſh, and his bloud, it's cleare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that hee had likewiſe an humane nature too, even hee tooke part likewiſe, ſaith the<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14.</note> Apoſtle, of the ſame fleſh and bloud with the reſt of the children, and ſo became<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30.</note> fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone, and all this too, not in<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ignat. ad Philip. p. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> opinion onely, and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as the old exploded<note n="c" place="margin">Vide Eſtium ad cap. <hi>2.</hi> in Philip. ver. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>79.</hi>
               </note> Marcionites and Manichees conceited, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaith, but Really, and in Truth; for ſo the Scripture plainely, The word was [<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14.</note> made] fleſh, Made, I ſay, and that not brought downe along with him
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1079:38"/> out of heaven, as the Apollinarian Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes imagined, but made out of the fleſh of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, Gal. 4.4. <hi>Factus
[ex] muliere,</hi> made [of] a woman; for that prepoſition <hi>[ex]</hi> or [of] noteth the materiall cauſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, and that our Lord and Saviour was <hi>ſubſtantialiter factus,</hi> as<note n="d" place="margin">Theophyl. ad <hi>1.</hi> Mat. ver. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theophylact</hi> notes, made of the very ſubſtance of the Virgin; which overthroweth alſo that Valentinian hereſie, which taught that Chriſt paſſed onely as water through a conduit-pipe, through her wombe, but took nothing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of her ſubſtance; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> elſewhere <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3. ſaith expreſly, that he was made [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, [of] the ſeed of <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh; <hi>[Factum] propriâ ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione intellige,</hi> ſaith<note n="e" place="margin">Beza ad Rom. <hi>1.</hi> ver. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Beza,</hi> the word [made] is there properly to be underſtood, as ſhewing the very ſubſtance of Chriſts fleſh to be made of the very ſubſtance of the Virgins: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, had it not been ſo, he could never have been capable of<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14.</note> Death, or ſuffering, thereby to overcome him that had the power of Death, the Devill, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſputes moſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1079:39"/> ſtrongly; the Godhead being, as not paſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate (as the Vorſtian blaſphemie was) ſo neither paſsible, or ſubject unto death, or ſhedding of bloud,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22.</note> without which yet there was no remiſsion of ſinnes poſsible: Sometimes indeed the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking <hi>in concreto</hi> of Chriſts Perſon, which had uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it a twofold Nature, by that which Divines call a Communication of proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that is given to the whole perſon which is proper onely <hi>in abſtracto,</hi> to the one nature. So we read Act. 20.28. [God] is ſaid to have purchaſed the Church with his owne
[bloud,] Now God himſelfe is a<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24.</note> Spirit, ſaith the Scripture, and a Spirit, ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, hath not fleſh, and bones, as yee ſee me have, Luk. 24.39. and if there be no fleſh, nor veines to hold and containe bloud, which for the remiſsion of ſinnes<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22.</note> muſt be ſhed, then ſurely there can be no purchaſe of the Church by bloud: therefore that ſpeech and the like, in the language of the Scripture, is to be underſtood in Trope, or ſacred Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, not ſtrictly, and abſtractively; no more then that Text in St. <hi>John</hi> muſt be, Joh. 3.13.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1079:39"/> where Chriſt ſpeaking of himſelfe, as the Son of Man, ſaith that he
[is] in Heaven, when yet he there ſpake upon the earth, as man, to <hi>Nicodemus:</hi> it muſt therefore be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by Communication of properties, and <hi>in concreto,</hi> it being True, that that divine Perſon which by an admirable union had Two Natures united to its ſelfe, did, and was thus, or thus, as Gods Spirit in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is pleaſed to expreſſe ſo deep, and great a myſtery.</p>
            <p>Thus ye ſee, that if there were no other Texts to prove it, yet from this one the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Two Natures of Chriſt hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatically united to his Divine Perſon, would bee ſufficiently collected. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this point is hence but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee diſcourſed of, this being rather the <hi>hypotheſis,</hi> then the <hi>theſis</hi> of the Text directly; I rather come to ſhew how, and by what ſinewes the Reſurrection of Beleevers is from hence deducible; and this is founded upon Two maine grounds: Firſt, becauſe Chriſt himſelfe being the<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22.</note> Head of his Church, and every Beleever a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1079:40"/> lively member of his body, by vertue of the myſticall, and effectuall Union that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the head and the members, as the head is raiſed, ſo ſhall the members like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Beſides, Chriſt is as the <hi>Primitiae,</hi> the firſt-fruits, as Saint<note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, wee as the reſt of the whole lumpe; looke now, as the dedication of the firſt-fruits of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe did unto the Jewes conſecrate, and in a manner ſanctifie the whole other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, even ſo our Saviour by his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, hath conſecrated unto all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers theirs, <hi>Cùm eadem ſit ratio primitiarum, &amp; totius cumuli,</hi> as<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza ad</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> noteth, there being the ſame reaſon, by this conſequence, of the whole lumpe, and of the firſt-fruits. The wicked ſhall indeed bee rayſed up too, but unto everlaſting ſhame, confuſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel,</hi> and Saint<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.29.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> ſay, by the [power] of God, but the beleever, and his True member onely by vertue of his ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall merit, and Communion: [I] <hi>will raiſe him up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other thing to be noted, is the Time mentioned for this raiſing up, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:1079:40"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, at the laſt Day; he meanes, the day of our common<note n="p" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</note> appearance before him, wherein the heavens being on fire, ſhall be<note n="q" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12.</note> diſſolved, and the elements ſhall melt with fervent heat: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it by an <hi>emphaſis,</hi>
[<note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
[that] day, that ſo remarkable, that ſo<note n="b" place="margin">Jud. ver. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> great, and dreadfull day of<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.12.</note> account: by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> it is called the day of the<note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.</note> Lord; Then it is that Chriſt will raiſe up the Beleever, even at the [laſt] day of the world, after which both day and time ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>This is a ſentence, which like the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous wine in Cana of Galilee, is ſet down as the beſt till<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.10.</note> laſt; and is indeed like to King <hi>Davids</hi> wine, that which maketh<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15.</note> glad the heart of every righteous man, who if in this life onely he had hope, he were of all men elſe moſt<note n="g" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19.</note> miſerable: For as the life of an unbeleever is like a Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, which is preſented in with Muſick, and all expreſsions of jollity, but it goes off uſually in a diſmall, and a ſad cataſtrophe; ſo is the life of a Beleever to a Comedie, which though brought upon the ſtage in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1079:41"/> blackes, under ſad lookes, ſoft paces, faint ſpeeches, and ſuch like emblemes of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, yet ſtay a while, and ye ſhall ſee all goe off in mirth and muſicke; the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, when the other calls for the rockes, and mountaines to fall upon him, and to ſhelter him from the wrath of the Lambe in vaine, ſhall at that [laſt] day, being rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up by his head Chriſt Jeſus, lift up his head with joy, becauſe that his Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.28.</note> draweth nigh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will raiſe him up at the laſt day:</hi> that is, as<note n="i" place="margin">Rupertus ad cap. <hi>6.</hi> Joh.</note> 
               <hi>Rupertus</hi> gloſſeth, <hi>à congerie aeternâ morte mortuorum, ex nomine eum vocans, diſcernam,</hi> I will ſegregate him from the whole other maſſe, or drove, as it were, of wicked men, that ſhall dye eternally for their impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie in ſinne, and call him forth by name, and will not bee<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32, 33.</note> aſhamed to owne him then at that laſt day, who was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of his reproach, in his warfare againſt the world, the fleſh, and the Divell here below. So True is that of King <hi>David,</hi> that if we marke the perfect man, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the upright, wee ſhall finde that the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1079:41"/> [end] of that man is peace; but the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors ſhall be deſtroyed together, and the [end] of the wicked ſhall be cut off, Pſ. 37. 37, 38. conferre Eccl. 8.12, 13. Pſ. 92.7. Mal. 3.17, 18. Wherefore, let us comfort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with theſe words, as well knowing that howſoever the righteous ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed by afflictions, yet it is but on the [<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.31.</note> earth] ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> and no farther, the end of their dayes, is the day of the end of all their ſorrow, and miſery, for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>To conclude, let the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29.</note> thought then of our ends, bee ſtill the end of our thoughts: and that our end may bee good, let us bee ſure that wee have good ends in all our projects, and our Chriſtian performances, or<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 7.36.</note> undertakings, before that laſt end of all comes, Then ſhall we indeed be rayſed up with joy, and comfort moſt unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, at that laſt Day.</p>
            <p>The meanes to accompliſh this, is, To propound our Saviours Reſurrection as a Patterne of ours, in our ſpirituall<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14.</note> awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out of the ſleep of ſinne, by our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1079:42"/> and as S. <hi>John</hi> hath phraſed it, Our<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6, 7.</note> firſt Reſurrection: Now before Chriſts, there was an<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.2.</note> earthquake, ſo in our Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration there is a conquaſſation uſually, and a ſhaking of the ſoule, a<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.29.</note> trembling of the conſcience, through a ſight of ſinne, and of our miſery thereby; the day of our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, muſt be like the day of our firſt birth, <hi>Dies lachrymoſa,</hi> a Day of<note n="g" place="margin">Ingreſſus ſlebilis, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſus debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, egreſſus horribilis. <hi>Ber.</hi>
               </note> Teares, ſhed in contrition for our ſinnes paſt; when wee muſt, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did the<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.6.</note> rock in Horeb, ſtrike the rocks of our too too obdurate hearts with a rod of remorſe, that from thence may flow out even rivers, and ſtreames of ſorrow for our looſe converſations before calling: The continuall dropping of this water hollowes the ſtone, mollifies and ſoftens the heart, preparing it aright to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſeeds of grace. One ſting of the fiery Serpent in the wilderneſſe drives the pained Iſraelite to look up for remedy to the<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 21.9.</note> braſen Serpent, there ſet up: ſo when the Conſcience is, as it were, ſtung with the bitings of the<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9.</note> old Serpent the Devill, by the ſight, and ſmart for ſinne, Then flies
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1079:42"/> the Penitent, and ſobbing ſoule for eaſe, and remedy to the True braſen<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.14.</note> Serpent Chriſt Jeſus, who hath broken the teeth, and plucked out that<note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 57.</note> ſting which ſo much pained the good ſoule. The<note n="n" place="margin">Initium ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis, notitia peccati: qui peccare ſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcit, corrigi non vult. <hi>Sen.</hi> —Fruſtra me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantis auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium expectat, qui vulnus non detegit. <hi>Boctius.</hi>
               </note> ſight, and ſenſe of miſery by ſinne is the ſure prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory meanes to ſeek, and finde a remedy by mercy; as when the powers of the jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors ſoule were ſhaken, with as ſtrong an earth-quake, as the Priſon it ſelfe was, Then, but not till then, hee<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.29. Non poteſt ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quo modo morbos curare conveniat, qui undè hi ſunt, ignorat. <hi>Cornel. Celſ. de Re Med. lib.</hi> 1.</note> ſprang in to <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> deſiring both eaſe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, from the guilt of ſinne, unto the life of Chriſtianity: The like to which wee read of S. <hi>Peters</hi> Converts, when they were<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">A man were better feele wrath then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>D. Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> in ſick ſouls ſalve.</note> pricked in their hearts, then they cry out, What ſhall wee do to bee ſaved? 2. Secondly, Chriſts Reſurrection was<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 54<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Integrall,</hi> whole in every part, a moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete, and perfect Reſurrection; he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting, or defective in his body, which now aroſe <hi>in incorruptibilitate,</hi> as<note n="r" place="margin">Primaſius in <hi>1.</hi> ad Corinth. c. <hi>15.</hi> v. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Primaſius</hi> ſpeaks, in an abſolute incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea, and impoſsibility of returning back againe to Death, He being riſen dieth
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1079:43"/> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.9.</note> no more, death hath no more dominion over him; for he aroſe <hi>Immortalis Totaliter,</hi> as<note n="p" place="margin">Raymund. à Sabunde, in Theolog. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural.</note> 
               <hi>Raymundus à Sabunde</hi> ſaith, Totally Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall. Now his Reſurrection being an example of ours, from hence wee are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to a Totall, Integrall, and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall abrenunciation of all ſinne, unto the contrary reformation. A Chriſtian muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whole in regard of ſincerity, univerſall in regard of the extent of his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, unto<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.128.</note> all Gods Commandements; for hee that allowes himſelfe in any one knowne ſinne, cannot bee ſaid Truly to hate any ſinne; even as a looſe adulterer that hath many curtiſans, but ſome one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reſt, on whom hee doates, on whom his luxurious affections are more intenſively enamoured, though hee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the reſt but onely in a generall ſalute, and ſo goes them all by, to glut himſelfe with pleaſure on that one: Though the manifeſtation of his carnall love be greater to this one, then to all the other, yet hee cannot properly be ſaid to hate any of the reſt: But a Chriſtian muſt not onely, as
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1079:43"/> 
               <hi>Herod,</hi> be at his [<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.20.</note> many] things, nor as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa,</hi> at his [<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.28.</note> almoſt,] nor as <hi>Naaman,</hi> at his Rimmon, and his being pardoned in [<note n="t" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.18.</note>This] though but an onely minion: but he that is in Chriſt muſt bee a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture throughout, and<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.29.</note> altogether;<note n="x" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.</note> all things muſt become New, in heart and affection, in life and converſation, in body, in ſoule, in ſpirit,<note n="y" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23.</note> Wholly, Integrally, Univerſally; for ſo was Chriſts Reſurrection. 3. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Chriſt aroſe ſpeedily, the<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.46.</note> Third day from his death; and that no ſooner, nor no later: firſt, ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Thom. <hi>3<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
                  </hi> qu. <hi>53.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi> in corp.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas,</hi> to ſhew the Truth of both his Natures; it behoved him to riſe quickly, leaſt if his Reſurrection had beene deferred till the end of the world, the Truth of his Divinity might, with his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency, have beene ſuſpected, as if hee<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>See John</hi> 10.18.</note> could not have raiſed up himſelfe before; and it behoved him to lie till the third day before hee aroſe, leaſt the Truth of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and his death might have beene queſtioned; now continuing in the grave untill the Third Day, (ſo that the grave to our Saviour was not onely Sheol, but alſo
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1079:44"/> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Bp. Lake, quà ſupra. p. <hi>152.</hi>
               </note> Shacath, not onely a greedy ſwallower, but a ravenous digeſter alſo) it's manifeſt, that his Death was True; No Apoplectick extaſie being compatible with life, (under favour) above three dayes. Secondly, Hee roſe the third day, that is, ſpeedily, no long delay intervening betweene his Diſſolution, and his Reſurrection; to bee a Patterne to us herein of our ſpeedy, and<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.1.</note> early ariſing out of the grave of ſinne unto the life of grace; <hi>Ne differas de die in diem,</hi> ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Siraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> Make no tarrying to turne to the Lord, and put not off from day to day. I love them that love me, ſaith God, and they that ſeeke me early ſhall finde me, Prov. 8.17. God loves ſuch as bee <hi>aurorantes ad ſe,</hi> that with the firſt peeping of the day give up themſelves to God: Let us with <hi>Abel</hi> offer up the<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4.</note> firſtlings of our Time, in Sacrifice to God, we ſhall [ſo] be the firſt in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation: Let us die the wooll of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy and youth, into the graine colour of ſanctity, that when our dayes are woven into more yeares, wee may never after change colour. Awake up my glory, ſaith
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1079:44"/> King <hi>David,</hi> awake Pſaltery, and Harpe, I my ſelfe will awake right early, Pſal. 57.8. Or, as ſome render it, <hi>Excitabo auroram,</hi> I will ſtirre up the morning, <hi>non illam ut me à ſomno excitet praeſtolabor, ſed illam ego morantem exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabo,</hi> ſaith<note n="m" place="margin">Granatenſ. tom. <hi>3.</hi> concion. de temp. conc. <hi>1.</hi> in die S. Paſch.</note> 
               <hi>Granatenſis.</hi> And ſurely, my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Chriſtians, would wee, as now it's<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.11.</note> high time, awake out of the ſleepe of our carnall ſecurity and ſin; and as <hi>Bildad</hi> advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Job,</hi> ſeek unto God [<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 8.5, 6.</note> betimes,] ſurely now he would awake for us, and make the habitation of our righteouſneſſe proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: Yea, if thus we would awake, and ariſe from the dead, in the firſt Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Chriſt himſelfe ſhall give us<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.14.</note> light; that is, himſelfe: for ſo old <hi>Simeon</hi> calleth him, The<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.32. <hi>&amp; Joh.</hi> 1.9.</note> Light to lighten the Gentiles; and, in thy<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9.</note> light, O bleſſed and ſweet Saviour, we ſhall ſurely ſee light.</p>
            <p>This was the way that a<note n="*" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Peterſon, the reverend Dean of Exeter, in his learned and elegant ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon upon Eph. <hi>5.14</hi> preached in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall of Saint Peter there, upon Eaſter day <hi>1639</hi>
               </note> bright ſtarre pointed out unto me lately, as yee all know, and the readieſt affections of mine heart, lending mee winde and ſayles at will for preſent, would now put mee on to ſteare amayne in the ſame courſe: This was the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1079:45"/> Muſick that ſo tooke our eares, and hearts, upon the ſolemne Feſtivall it ſelfe: Oh that as the voice and eccho in the woods, that moſt divine Sermon, and our true Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, might make up one ſound, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination!</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, my meditations have, ſince that time, as <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.1.</note> ſtayed long upon it; and were it not that I juſtly feared my jarring notes would marre that taking harmony, I could yet winde up mine inſtrument a while longer; but ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine an <hi>Orpheus</hi> could not but draw even the ſtony heart to follow: Doe then, what then you heard; I will aſſure you, it is that which leads the way directly to the life eternal, in this my Text: Concerning which, if ye would now enquire of me, and aske me what it is, I muſt needs tell you, that its that, which ſooner ſwallowes up our thoughts in wonder, then it can become capable of but a competent expreſsion by our ſpeech: its better knowne indeed by True fruition, then diſcourſe: Therefore leaving that, let us now rather all pray, ſo
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1079:45"/> to bee enabled all to feed upon the fleſh, and to drinke the bloud of Chriſt by faith, that in the iſſue, we may make ſure of the full fruition of the ſame; and in the end of all things, obtaine infallibly the<note n="c" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9.</note> end of all our faith, even the ſalvation of our ſoules; and this through the alone merits and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of the ſame Jeſus Chriſt the<note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1.</note> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, who hath riſen from the dead, is<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8, 9.</note> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up into Heaven, there to<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.3.</note> prepare thoſe eternall manſions of bliſſe, promiſed to all that cleave unto him by a true, effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, and lively faith, even for ever and ever. Unto him, with thee, O righteous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thy bleſſed incomprehenſible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, our God in Unity, our God in Trinity, be all honour, and praiſe, thankſgiving, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, dominion, ſalvation, and glory in the<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.21.</note> Church, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ages, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
